<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.1">
<book code="PRO" style="id">- unfoldingWord Simplified -</book>
<para style="h">Proverbs</para>
<para style="toc1">Proverbs</para>
<para style="toc2">Proverbs</para>
<para style="mt1">Proverbs</para>
<chapter number="1" style="c" sid="PRO 1"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 1:1"/>{These are} the wise sayings said by Solomon. {He was} David’s son and Israel’s king.<verse eid="PRO 1:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 1:2"/>{These wise sayings are} for knowing what is wise and instructive. {They are} for understanding insightful things that people say.<verse eid="PRO 1:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 1:3"/>{These wise sayings are} for instructing someone about what is insightful, righteous, just, and honest.<verse eid="PRO 1:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 1:4"/>{They are} for making naive people prudent, and {for making} young people knowledgeable and discreet.<verse eid="PRO 1:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 1:5"/>(Wise people will listen {to these wise sayings} and learn more. Indeed, understanding people will know {what to do} because these sayings will guide them.)<verse eid="PRO 1:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 1:6"/>{These wise sayings are} for understanding wise sayings and parables. {Indeed, they are for understanding} what wise people say and the riddles they tell.<verse eid="PRO 1:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 1:7"/>Reverently fearing Yahweh is necessary for being knowledgeable. {But} foolish people detest what is wise or instructive.<verse eid="PRO 1:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 1:8"/>My child, listen carefully to what I, your father, am teaching you. Indeed, obey the rules that your mother has commanded.<verse eid="PRO 1:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 1:9"/>{Obey your parents’ teaching} because it {will make you respectable, as if it} were an attractive wreath on your head, or beautiful necklaces around your neck.<verse eid="PRO 1:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 1:10"/>My child, if sinful people tempt you {to sin with them}, refuse {to do so}.<verse eid="PRO 1:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 1:11"/>Those sinful people may say, “Join us! We will hide and wait in order to kill someone {who walks by}. Indeed, we will hide ourselves in order to suddenly attack an innocent person for no good reason.<verse eid="PRO 1:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 1:12"/>We will kill living people completely, as if we were death itself. {We will even kill} healthy people, as if they could not escape dying.<verse eid="PRO 1:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 1:13"/>We will discover many valuable treasures! We will fill our houses with what we steal!<verse eid="PRO 1:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 1:14"/>Join our gang! We will share all the loot between us.”<verse eid="PRO 1:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 1:15"/>My child, do not associate with those sinful people! Prevent yourself from doing anything they do!<verse eid="PRO 1:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 1:16"/>{Avoid those sinners} because they are eager to do wicked things. They even rush to murder people.<verse eid="PRO 1:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 1:17"/>It is useless {for a hunter} to put out a net {to trap a bird} while the bird is watching {because the bird will avoid the net}.<verse eid="PRO 1:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 1:18"/>However, {these sinful people are more foolish than birds.} They {actually} hide in wait, so that they kill themselves. Indeed, they hide themselves to suddenly attack, so that they die.<verse eid="PRO 1:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 1:19"/>That is what happens to anyone who gains wealth in an unjust manner. What they gained unjustly will kill them.<verse eid="PRO 1:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 1:20"/>What is wise {is like a woman who} calls out {to everyone} in public. Indeed, what is wise {is like a woman who} shouts {to people} in crowded places.<verse eid="PRO 1:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 1:21"/>Indeed, at the place where busy streets intersect she cries out. Indeed, at the {crowded} entrance of the city gates she speaks.<verse eid="PRO 1:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 1:22"/>She cries, “You naive people have loved being naive for too long! You people who ridicule have enjoyed ridiculing to benefit yourselves for too long! You foolish people have hated what you should know for too long!<verse eid="PRO 1:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 1:23"/>Turn around {and listen} to me when I correct you! Pay attention! I will tell you all that I am thinking. Indeed, I will help you understand what I am saying to you.<verse eid="PRO 1:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 1:24"/>I cried out {to you}, but you refused {to listen}. Indeed, I invited you to come to me, but no one paid any attention {to me}.<verse eid="PRO 1:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 1:25"/>You ignored everything I advised {you to do}. Indeed, you rejected what I said to correct you.<verse eid="PRO 1:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 1:26"/>Therefore, as for me, I will laugh at you when disastrous things happen to you. Indeed, I will ridicule you when you are terrified.<verse eid="PRO 1:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 1:27"/>{I will ridicule you} when you are terrified, as if a violent storm has arrived, {when} disastrous things happen to you violently, {and} when you become distressed and anguished!<verse eid="PRO 1:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 1:28"/>At that time, those foolish people will cry out to me {to help them}, but I will not reply {to them}. Indeed, they will desperately try to find me, but they will not be able to.<verse eid="PRO 1:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 1:29"/>{Those foolish people will not find me} because they refuse to be knowledgeable. They have also decided not to reverently fear Yahweh.<verse eid="PRO 1:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 1:30"/>Those foolish people rejected what I advised {them to do}. Indeed, they detested everything I said to correct them.<verse eid="PRO 1:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 1:31"/>Those foolish people will suffer rightly for what they have done. Indeed, they will suffer fully for what they have planned.<verse eid="PRO 1:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 1:32"/>Ultimately, naive people will die because they refuse {to be wise}. Indeed, being complacent will destroy foolish people.<verse eid="PRO 1:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 1:33"/>By contrast, people who listen attentively to what I say will live safely. They will not fear that something evil might happen to them.”<verse eid="PRO 1:33"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 1"/>
<chapter number="2" style="c" sid="PRO 2"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 2:1"/>My child, accept what I say. Consider what I command {you} to be precious.<verse eid="PRO 2:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 2:2"/>{Do this by} listening attentively to what is wise, {and by} thinking seriously about what you should understand.<verse eid="PRO 2:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 2:3"/>Yes, cry out to learn what you should understand. Cry loudly to learn what you should perceive!<verse eid="PRO 2:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 2:4"/>Try to learn what is wise, like you would try to find silver. Indeed, look eagerly for it, like you would look for a treasure that someone has hidden.<verse eid="PRO 2:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 2:5"/>{If you do those things,} then you will understand how to reverently fear Yahweh. You will even succeed in knowing God.<verse eid="PRO 2:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 2:6"/>{This is} because Yahweh provides people with what is wise. He tells them what they should know and understand.<verse eid="PRO 2:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 2:7"/>He gives what is truly wise to upright people. He protects people who behave honestly.<verse eid="PRO 2:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 2:8"/>{He does these things} in order to guard those people who live justly. Indeed, he keeps safe those people who are faithful to him.<verse eid="PRO 2:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 2:9"/>{If you listen to me,} then you will understand what is righteous, just, and honest, {even} the best way to behave.<verse eid="PRO 2:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 2:10"/>{This is because} you will truly know what is wise, and knowing what you should know will please you.<verse eid="PRO 2:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 2:11"/>Being discreet will make you safe. Indeed, being insightful will make you secure.<verse eid="PRO 2:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 2:12"/>{Being like this will protect you} in order to save you from people who behave wickedly {and save you} from people who speak perversely.<verse eid="PRO 2:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 2:13"/>Those people refuse to behave righteously in order to behave wickedly.<verse eid="PRO 2:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 2:14"/>They gladly do evil things. They enjoy evil and perverse acts.<verse eid="PRO 2:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 2:15"/>They behave deceptively. Indeed, they act deviously.<verse eid="PRO 2:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 2:16"/>{Being discreet and insightful will protect you also} in order to save you from adulterous women, {and to save you} from immoral women who speak {to you} seductively.<verse eid="PRO 2:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 2:17"/>Those women left the husbands they married when they were young. They even forgot what they had promised to God {when they married}.<verse eid="PRO 2:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 2:18"/>{Being discreet and insightful will rescue you} because {going to} such a woman’s house will result in you dying. Indeed, going with her will result in you going to the place where the spirits of dead people are.<verse eid="PRO 2:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 2:19"/>No one who acts adulterously with her will live again. They will never become alive again!<verse eid="PRO 2:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 2:20"/>Therefore, behave like a good person. Indeed, conduct yourself like a righteous person.<verse eid="PRO 2:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 2:21"/>Ultimately, people who live uprightly will live in our land, Indeed, people whom Yahweh does not blame {for acting wickedly} will stay in this land for a long time.<verse eid="PRO 2:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 2:22"/>By contrast, Yahweh will remove people who act wickedly from our land. Yahweh will completely remove people who act treacherously from this land!<verse eid="PRO 2:22"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 2"/>
<chapter number="3" style="c" sid="PRO 3"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 3:1"/>My child, remember the rules I have taught you! Always be mindful to obey what I have commanded you!<verse eid="PRO 3:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 3:2"/>{Do this} because {obeying} what I have commanded you will help you live for a long time with many fulfilling and peaceful years.<verse eid="PRO 3:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 3:3"/>Always be faithful and trustworthy. Let everyone see {how faithful and trustworthy you are, as if} they were a necklace you are wearing. Remember to be faithful and trustworthy at all times.<verse eid="PRO 3:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 3:4"/>As a result of doing so, both God and people will approve of you and think well of you.<verse eid="PRO 3:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 3:5"/>Trust Yahweh completely, and do not rely on what you understand.<verse eid="PRO 3:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 3:6"/>Remember Yahweh whenever you do anything. As a result {of doing so}, he will show you what you should do.<verse eid="PRO 3:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 3:7"/>Do not think that you are wise. Instead, reverently fear Yahweh and refuse to do what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 3:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 3:8"/>Doing so will make your body healthy. Indeed, {doing so} will refresh you.<verse eid="PRO 3:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 3:9"/>Revere Yahweh {by giving to him} some of your riches, {even by giving to him} some of the first {crops} from everything that you harvest.<verse eid="PRO 3:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 3:10"/>{Doing so} will result in your places for storing crops becoming abundantly full {of crops}. Even your containers for wine will overflow with fresh wine.<verse eid="PRO 3:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 3:11"/>My child, do not refuse to listen when Yahweh corrects you. Do not be resentful even when he rebukes you.<verse eid="PRO 3:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 3:12"/>{Do not do so} because Yahweh only reproves the people whom he loves. He is similar to a father who reproves the child whom he likes.<verse eid="PRO 3:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 3:13"/>People who gain what is wise are happy. Indeed, people who gain what they should understand {are truly happy}.<verse eid="PRO 3:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 3:14"/>{This is} because being wise profits people more than silver {could profit them}. Indeed, being wise benefits people more than gold {could benefit them}.<verse eid="PRO 3:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 3:15"/>Being wise is more valuable than precious jewels. There is nothing you could desire that is worth as much as being wise.<verse eid="PRO 3:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 3:16"/>Being wise will help you live for a long time. Being wise will help you become wealthy and honorable.<verse eid="PRO 3:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 3:17"/>Being wise will make you live pleasantly. Indeed, in every way being wise will make you live peacefully.<verse eid="PRO 3:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 3:18"/>What is wise is {like} a tree {with fruit} that keeps alive the people who hold on to it, People who are consistently wise live happily.<verse eid="PRO 3:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 3:19"/>Yahweh made the world by using what is wise. He made the sky by using what he understands.<verse eid="PRO 3:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 3:20"/>According to what Yahweh understands, water flowed forth from deep {below the earth} and water fell from the clouds {above}.<verse eid="PRO 3:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 3:21"/>My child, always remember to do what is prudent and discreet. Always be mindful to do those things.<verse eid="PRO 3:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 3:22"/>Doing so will help you live for a long time and will make you {respectable, as if you had} an attractive necklace around your neck.<verse eid="PRO 3:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 3:23"/>Doing so will {also} cause you to live safely. You will not even get hurt.<verse eid="PRO 3:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 3:24"/>When you lie down {to sleep}, you will not fear anything. You will even lie down {to sleep} and sleep peacefully.<verse eid="PRO 3:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 3:25"/>Do not worry about something terrible suddenly happening {to you}, or about {what will happen} when God destroys wicked people.<verse eid="PRO 3:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 3:26"/>{Do not worry} because Yahweh will make you confident. He will not allow people to harm you.<verse eid="PRO 3:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 3:27"/>Do not refrain from giving what is good to people who deserve it when you are able to do so.<verse eid="PRO 3:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 3:28"/>When you have something {that someone you know needs}, do not tell that person, “Go away and come back later. I will give it to you then.”<verse eid="PRO 3:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 3:29"/>Do not plan to harm anyone, even someone who lives nearby and trusts you.<verse eid="PRO 3:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 3:30"/>Do not argue needlessly with someone who has not harmed you.<verse eid="PRO 3:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 3:31"/>Do not envy violent people. Do not imitate anything they do.<verse eid="PRO 3:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 3:32"/>{Do not do so} because Yahweh detests {such} people who act wickedly, but he converses like a friend with people who act uprightly.<verse eid="PRO 3:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 3:33"/>Yahweh causes bad things to happen to the families of wicked people, but he causes good things to happen to the families of righteous people.<verse eid="PRO 3:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="PRO 3:34"/>Yahweh is the one who ridicules people who ridicule {others}, but he approves of people who are humble.<verse eid="PRO 3:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="PRO 3:35"/>People will honor wise people, but will shame foolish people.<verse eid="PRO 3:35"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 3"/>
<chapter number="4" style="c" sid="PRO 4"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 4:1"/>Children, listen carefully to what I, your father, am teaching you. Pay attention in order to learn what you should understand.<verse eid="PRO 4:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 4:2"/>{Do this} because what I am teaching you is good. {So} remember the rules that I am teaching you.<verse eid="PRO 4:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 4:3"/>I was once my father’s boy, {and} my mother considered me to be her delicate, only son.<verse eid="PRO 4:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 4:4"/>During that time, my father taught me. He told me, “Remember what I have told you! Do what I have commanded you, so that you will keep on living!<verse eid="PRO 4:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 4:5"/>Obtain what is wise and what you should understand! Always remember what I have spoken to you!<verse eid="PRO 4:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 4:6"/>Remember what is wise, so that it will be like a woman who keeps you safe. Love what is wise, so that it will be like a woman who protects you.<verse eid="PRO 4:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 4:7"/>Being wise is the most important thing! {So} obtain what is wise! {Even if} it costs you everything that you own, obtain what you should understand!<verse eid="PRO 4:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 4:8"/>Prize what is wise, so that you will become great. People will honor you when you value what is wise.<verse eid="PRO 4:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 4:9"/>Being wise {will make you respectable, as if it} put an attractive wreath on your head. Indeed, being wise {will make you honorable, as if it} gave you a magnificent crown.”<verse eid="PRO 4:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 4:10"/>My child, listen attentively and accept what I say. Doing so will increase the number of years that you live.<verse eid="PRO 4:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 4:11"/>I instructed you in how to act wisely. I directed you in how to act uprightly.<verse eid="PRO 4:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 4:12"/>When you do something, nothing will prevent you {from succeeding}. Indeed, if you do anything, you will succeed.<verse eid="PRO 4:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 4:13"/>Consistently remember the things I have instructed you; keep remembering them! Always be mindful of them, because they will keep you alive.<verse eid="PRO 4:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 4:14"/>Do not do what wicked people do. Indeed, do not act like evil people act.<verse eid="PRO 4:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 4:15"/>Shun doing what is evil. Do not even consider doing it! Refuse to act wickedly and do something else.<verse eid="PRO 4:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 4:16"/>{Do not act wickedly} because {it is as if} evil people cannot even sleep unless they do something evil; {it is as if} they cannot rest unless they hurt someone.<verse eid="PRO 4:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 4:17"/>{Do not act wickedly} because evil people do wicked things as if they were eating food; they violently hurt others as if they were drinking wine.<verse eid="PRO 4:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 4:18"/>As for righteous people, {they will live wisely and safely} like the light of the sun at dawn. {They will live more and more wisely and safely as} the sun shines brighter and brighter until the brightest time of day.<verse eid="PRO 4:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 4:19"/>{But} wicked people {live dangerously} like people {who walk} in total darkness. {Like people walking in darkness do not know} what they trip over, they do not know {what hurts them}.<verse eid="PRO 4:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 4:20"/>My child, pay attention to what I am saying to you! Listen carefully to what I say!<verse eid="PRO 4:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 4:21"/>Always remember what I say! Fully commit yourself to remembering such things!<verse eid="PRO 4:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 4:22"/>{Do this} because those who do so will live {for a long time}, even their whole bodies will be healthy.<verse eid="PRO 4:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 4:23"/>Be extremely careful about what you think, because what you think will control how you live.<verse eid="PRO 4:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 4:24"/>Do not say anything  that deceives people. Indeed, never say anything that misleads people.<verse eid="PRO 4:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 4:25"/>{Focus on doing what is right, like} someone who is always looking straight ahead. Indeed, {act like} someone who is looking straight in front of himself.<verse eid="PRO 4:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 4:26"/>Carefully consider what you do. As a result {of doing so}, you will succeed in everything that you do.<verse eid="PRO 4:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 4:27"/>Do not do anything other than what is right. Prevent yourself from doing what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 4:27"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 4"/>
<chapter number="5" style="c" sid="PRO 5"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 5:1"/>My son, pay attention to the wise things that I tell you! Listen carefully to what I say you should understand!<verse eid="PRO 5:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 5:2"/>{Do this} so that you may remain discreet, and you may preserve what you know when you speak.<verse eid="PRO 5:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 5:3"/>{Do this} because what adulterous women say seems delightful like honey and more pleasing than olive oil.<verse eid="PRO 5:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 5:4"/>However, being with such a woman will result in you being miserable, as if you had eaten a bitter plant. {You will suffer} like a person whom someone has cut with a sharp, double-edged sword.<verse eid="PRO 5:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 5:5"/>{Being with such a woman will result in both of you dying} as if she were leading you to where dead people are. Indeed, what she does will cause you both to die.<verse eid="PRO 5:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 5:6"/>She does not want to do what will cause her to live for a long time. She does not realize that she {lives precariously like someone who} is walking on an uneven path.<verse eid="PRO 5:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 5:7"/>So now, children, pay attention to what I say! Always remember what I have spoken to you!<verse eid="PRO 5:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 5:8"/>Stay far away from any adulterous woman! Do not even go near the door of the place where such a woman dwells!<verse eid="PRO 5:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 5:9"/>If you go to such a woman, people will weaken you, and some merciless person will take away {what you have gained in} the best time of your life.<verse eid="PRO 5:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 5:10"/>If you go to such a woman, people you do not know will satisfy themselves with {what you gained} when you were strong, and some foreign person will fill his house with what you labored to gain.<verse eid="PRO 5:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 5:11"/>Then you will groan when you are about to die and have worn out your whole body.<verse eid="PRO 5:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 5:12"/>Then you will say, “I hated it extremely when people corrected me! Indeed, I scorned people when they rebuked me!<verse eid="PRO 5:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 5:13"/>I did not obey the people who taught me. Indeed, I did not listen carefully to the people who instructed me.<verse eid="PRO 5:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 5:14"/>I almost utterly disgraced myself in public.”<verse eid="PRO 5:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 5:15"/>{So be like} someone who only drinks water from his own well; have sex with your wife only.<verse eid="PRO 5:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 5:16"/>{Do not be like} someone who lets his water run out into the streets; never have sex with other women!<verse eid="PRO 5:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 5:17"/>Only have sex with your own wife! Do not have sex with other women!<verse eid="PRO 5:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 5:18"/>Be happy with your wife; rejoice with the woman whom you married when you were young.<verse eid="PRO 5:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 5:19"/>{She is as beautiful as} a loving deer and {as graceful as} a mountain goat. Let how attractive she is always satisfy you. Constantly be exhilarated by how she loves you.<verse eid="PRO 5:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 5:20"/>My son, you should never be exhilarated by an adulterous woman! You should never passionately caress an immoral woman!<verse eid="PRO 5:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 5:21"/>{Never do that] because Yahweh fully knows what people do. Indeed, he knows everything that people do.<verse eid="PRO 5:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 5:22"/>The wicked things that wicked people do are {like} traps that catch them; the sinful things they do are {like] ropes that tie them down.<verse eid="PRO 5:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 5:23"/>Those wicked people will die because they did not discipline themselves. They will do what kills them because they are extremely foolish.<verse eid="PRO 5:23"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 5"/>
<chapter number="6" style="c" sid="PRO 6"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 6:1"/>My child, if you guarantee to pay a loan for someone you know, {or if} you agree to pay a loan for someone you do not know,<verse eid="PRO 6:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 6:2"/>{or if} you have troubled yourself by promising to do something, {and} you cannot fulfill what you promised,<verse eid="PRO 6:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 6:3"/>then, my child, do this in order to save yourself {from what you have troubled yourself with}: humbly go to that person you know and beg him {to cancel what you have promised} because he controls you.<verse eid="PRO 6:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 6:4"/>Do not sleep, do not even rest {until you go and talk to him}.<verse eid="PRO 6:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 6:5"/>Save yourself {immediately}, as if you were a deer fleeing from a hunter or a bird fleeing from a trapper.<verse eid="PRO 6:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 6:6"/>You lazy person, go watch ants! Consider what ants do so that you can be wise.<verse eid="PRO 6:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 6:7"/>Absolutely no one tells ants what to do.<verse eid="PRO 6:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 6:8"/>{Nevertheless,} at the right time they store their food {to eat during the winter}. Indeed, when people harvest crops, the ants collect what they will {later} eat.<verse eid="PRO 6:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 6:9"/>{But} you lazy person, stop sleeping! Wake up!<verse eid="PRO 6:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 6:10"/>{You say to yourself,} “Let me sleep just a little more! Let me lay my hands {across my chest} in order to rest comfortably for a little while longer!”<verse eid="PRO 6:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 6:11"/>{Being so lazy} will result in you suddenly becoming poor and needy as if a thief has robbed you.<verse eid="PRO 6:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 6:12"/>Worthless people who act sinfully constantly deceive people by what they say.<verse eid="PRO 6:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 6:13"/>They gesture with their bodies to deceive people.<verse eid="PRO 6:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 6:14"/>They are always thinking perversely while planning how to do evil things. They cause people to argue {with each other}.<verse eid="PRO 6:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 6:15"/>Because of this, disastrous things will suddenly happen to those people. Someone will destroy them instantly and they will not be able to recover.<verse eid="PRO 6:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 6:16"/>Yahweh absolutely hates six, no, seven things:<verse eid="PRO 6:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 6:17"/>being proud, speaking falsely, someone who murders a person who has not done anything wrong,<verse eid="PRO 6:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 6:18"/>someone who plans ways to act sinfully, someone who is eager to act wickedly,<verse eid="PRO 6:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 6:19"/>someone who easily lies when testifying, and someone who causes members of the same family to argue.<verse eid="PRO 6:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 6:20"/>My child, be mindful to obey what I, your father, have commanded {you}. Indeed, obey the rules that your mother has commanded.<verse eid="PRO 6:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 6:21"/>Remember what we have taught you as if it were always a part of you. Indeed, {remember these lessons as if} you wore them like a necklace.<verse eid="PRO 6:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 6:22"/>What we have taught you will cause you to know what you should do each day. It will cause you to be safe when you sleep. It will even be instructive for you when you wake up {in the morning}.<verse eid="PRO 6:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 6:23"/>{This is so} because what I have commanded {you} is {like} a lamp {for you}. Indeed, the rules {we taught you} are {like} a light {to guide you}. When we rebuke you while instructing you, {we do that} so that you can do what will keep you alive.<verse eid="PRO 6:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 6:24"/>{We taught you these lessons} in order to prevent you from {going to} wicked women, {and to prevent you} from {believing} what  immoral women say seductively.<verse eid="PRO 6:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 6:25"/>Do not think lustfully about her beautiful body. Do not let her seduce you by the {flirtatious} way she looks at you.<verse eid="PRO 6:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 6:26"/>{Do not do so} because, although having sex with a prostitute only costs you the price of a cheap meal, an {adulterous} married woman will cause you to die.<verse eid="PRO 6:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 6:27"/>Fire will surely burn people who put it on their chests!<verse eid="PRO 6:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 6:28"/>Burning coals will surely burn the feet of people who step on them!<verse eid="PRO 6:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 6:29"/>It is similar with anyone who acts adulterously with a married woman. People will certainly punish anyone who does that.<verse eid="PRO 6:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 6:30"/>Nobody hates people who steal if they steal {food} in order to feed themselves when they are hungry.<verse eid="PRO 6:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 6:31"/>Nevertheless, if people catch thieves, those thieves must pay back seven times {as much as they stole to those whom they stole from}. They must give everything that they have {in order to repay what they stole}.<verse eid="PRO 6:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 6:32"/>By contrast, a man who acts adulterously with a woman does not think wisely. What he does will kill him!<verse eid="PRO 6:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 6:33"/>Someone will injure and disgrace him, and he will always be ashamed.<verse eid="PRO 6:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="PRO 6:34"/>{This is so} because the jealous husband will become furious. He will act mercilessly when he revenges himself {on the man who acted adulterously with his wife}.<verse eid="PRO 6:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="PRO 6:35"/>That jealous husband will not accept any money {to stop being furious}, no matter how much money you offer him.<verse eid="PRO 6:35"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 6"/>
<chapter number="7" style="c" sid="PRO 7"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 7:1"/>My son, obey what I have told you. Sincerely consider what I have commanded {you} to be precious.<verse eid="PRO 7:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 7:2"/>Do what I have commanded {you}, so that you will keep on living. Consider the rules I have taught you to be the most precious things you possess.<verse eid="PRO 7:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 7:3"/>{Always remember what I have commanded you as if} it were tied around your fingers. Remember it at all times!<verse eid="PRO 7:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 7:4"/>Love what is wise as if it were your sister. Indeed, love what you should understand as if it were a close relative.<verse eid="PRO 7:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 7:5"/>{Do this} so that you will be able to stay away from adulterous women, and {stay away} from immoral women who speak {to you} seductively.<verse eid="PRO 7:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 7:6"/>{I was} once {standing} near the window {in my house}, and I looked down {from above the street} through the shutters on the window.<verse eid="PRO 7:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 7:7"/>Then I observed {someone} among the naive people. I noticed among the youths a young man who does not think wisely.<verse eid="PRO 7:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 7:8"/>He walked down the street near the corner of {the road where} the adulterous woman {dwells}. Then he walked toward the place where she dwelled.<verse eid="PRO 7:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 7:9"/>(It was the time of day when night begins, {and then} it became dark.)<verse eid="PRO 7:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 7:10"/>Suddenly an adulterous woman approached the young man. She was wearing a prostitute’s clothing and intended to deceive {the young man}.<verse eid="PRO 7:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 7:11"/>(That woman spoke loudly and acted rebelliously. She never stayed at home.<verse eid="PRO 7:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 7:12"/>She {often} walked around the streets and public places. At the corner of any road she waited for someone whom she could seduce.)<verse eid="PRO 7:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 7:13"/>When {she saw the young man}, she firmly took hold of him and kissed him. She shamelessly told {him},<verse eid="PRO 7:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 7:14"/>“Today {I have meat in my house, because} I sacrificed an animal {in the temple} to promise friendship {with Yahweh}. {In this way} I did what I had vowed to do.<verse eid="PRO 7:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 7:15"/>So I have come out here to meet you. {I have come out} to look everywhere for you, and now I have found you!<verse eid="PRO 7:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 7:16"/>I have covered my bed with expensive Egyptian fabric.<verse eid="PRO 7:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 7:17"/>I have put pleasant-smelling perfumes on my bed: myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.<verse eid="PRO 7:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 7:18"/>Come {with me}! Let us satisfy ourselves sexually all night! Let us enjoy ourselves sexually!<verse eid="PRO 7:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 7:19"/>{Come with me} because my husband is not at home. He has gone away on a long journey.<verse eid="PRO 7:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 7:20"/>He filled a bag with money and took it with him. He will not return home until the middle of the month.”<verse eid="PRO 7:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 7:21"/>{Thus} that adulterous woman persuaded the young man by speaking so persuasively; by speaking seductively she allured him {into doing what she wanted to do}.<verse eid="PRO 7:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 7:22"/>He quickly followed her {to her home}. He {unknowingly} went to die like an ox going to the place where its owner will kill it. {He went to die} like a foolish person {who goes} in fetters to be punished<verse eid="PRO 7:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 7:23"/>until {someone kills him by} shooting an arrow into his entrails. {He went to die quickly} like a bird that flies into a trap. He did not realize that going with the adulterous woman would cause him to die.<verse eid="PRO 7:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 7:24"/>So now, children, pay attention to what I say! Pay careful attention to what I have spoken to you!<verse eid="PRO 7:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 7:25"/>Do not decide to do what adulterous women do. Indeed, never act like them!<verse eid="PRO 7:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 7:26"/>{Do not do so} because they have killed many men who are {now} slain. They have slain so many men!<verse eid="PRO 7:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 7:27"/>{Going to} an adulterous woman’s house is doing something that will result in that person dying. {Doing that} will result in that person going to the place where the spirits of dead people are.<verse eid="PRO 7:27"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 7"/>
<chapter number="8" style="c" sid="PRO 8"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 8:1"/>What is wise {is surely like a woman who} calls out {to everyone}. Indeed, what people should understand {is surely like a woman who} shouts {to people}.<verse eid="PRO 8:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 8:2"/>What is wise {is like a woman who} stands at the highest place along the crowded streets {where everyone can hear her}.<verse eid="PRO 8:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 8:3"/>What is wise {is like a woman who} cries out next to the gates at the entrance to a city.<verse eid="PRO 8:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 8:4"/>{She proclaims:} “I am calling out to all of you! I am speaking to all people!<verse eid="PRO 8:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 8:5"/>You naive people must comprehend what is prudent. You foolish people comprehend how to be discerning.<verse eid="PRO 8:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 8:6"/>Listen {to what I say}, because I will tell you some excellent things. I will speak to you about what is right.<verse eid="PRO 8:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 8:7"/>{Listen to what I say} because I speak what is true. I detest speaking what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 8:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 8:8"/>Everything that I say is righteous. I do not say anything that is false or deceptive.<verse eid="PRO 8:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 8:9"/>Everything that I say is plain for people who understand. {Everything that I say} is right to people who have become knowledgeable.<verse eid="PRO 8:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 8:10"/>Choose {to learn} what I instruct you instead of silver. Indeed, {choose to learn} what you should know instead of the finest gold.<verse eid="PRO 8:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 8:11"/>{Do this} because I am more valuable than precious jewels. I am more valuable than anything you can desire.<verse eid="PRO 8:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 8:12"/>I am what is wise. I am related to what is prudent. I enable someone to know what is discreet.<verse eid="PRO 8:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 8:13"/>Everyone who reverently fears Yahweh hates what is evil. {I hate it when} people are proud or arrogant. I hate it when people act wickedly and when people speak perversely.<verse eid="PRO 8:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 8:14"/>I advise people and enable them to be truly wise. I am what you need to understand. I strengthen people.<verse eid="PRO 8:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 8:15"/>I enable kings to rule {well}. {I enable} rulers to make righteous laws.<verse eid="PRO 8:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 8:16"/>I enable princes to govern; and {I enable} every royal official who judges righteously {to govern}.<verse eid="PRO 8:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 8:17"/>I {am what is wise, and} I benefit anyone who loves me. Anyone who earnestly tries to become wise will succeed.<verse eid="PRO 8:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 8:18"/>I enable people to become rich and I cause people to honor those people. {I enable people to have} riches that will last and {I enable people to become} righteous.<verse eid="PRO 8:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 8:19"/>What I can give people is more valuable than even the purest gold and the best silver.<verse eid="PRO 8:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 8:20"/>I {always} do what is righteous and just<verse eid="PRO 8:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 8:21"/>in order to give wealth to people who love me. I will fill up the places where they store valuable items.<verse eid="PRO 8:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 8:22"/>Yahweh had me{, what is wise,} when he began to create {everything}. {Indeed, he had me} before he started doing that.<verse eid="PRO 8:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 8:23"/>Yahweh established me a very long time ago—at the very beginning, before the world existed.<verse eid="PRO 8:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 8:24"/>I began to exist before the oceans existed and before there were springs abounding with water.<verse eid="PRO 8:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 8:25"/>I began to exist before Yahweh made the mountains {and} before the hills {existed}.<verse eid="PRO 8:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 8:26"/>{I began to exist} before Yahweh made the land or the fields or the first particles of dirt on the earth.<verse eid="PRO 8:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 8:27"/>I existed when Yahweh made the sky, {and} when he made the boundary between the sky and the ocean’s surface.<verse eid="PRO 8:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 8:28"/>{I existed} when Yahweh made the clouds above {the earth}, {and} when he made the springs flow at the bottom of the ocean.<verse eid="PRO 8:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 8:29"/>{I existed} when Yahweh set boundaries for the seas, so that the water {in the seas} would not go past those boundaries. {I existed} when Yahweh made the boundaries of the land.<verse eid="PRO 8:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 8:30"/>At that time I was {like} someone who was beside Yahweh {and} helped him create {everything}. I made him happy every day. I was always rejoicing when I was with him.<verse eid="PRO 8:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 8:31"/>{I was} rejoicing in the whole world that Yahweh had made. I was also happy with the people {he had made}.<verse eid="PRO 8:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 8:32"/>So now, children, pay attention to what I say! {Do this} because anyone who behaves wisely will be happy.<verse eid="PRO 8:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 8:33"/>Listen to what I teach {you}, so that you will become wise. Accept what I teach you!<verse eid="PRO 8:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="PRO 8:34"/>People who listen to me will be happy, {They are eager to listen to me like} people who wait {for me} at the door of my house every day. {They are like} people who diligently wait {for me} at my doorway.<verse eid="PRO 8:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="PRO 8:35"/>{This is true} because people who learn to be wise will live {a long time}, and Yahweh will approve of them.<verse eid="PRO 8:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="PRO 8:36"/>But those who refuse to be wise hurt themselves. All those who hate to be wise {are like people who} love death.”<verse eid="PRO 8:36"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 8"/>
<chapter number="9" style="c" sid="PRO 9"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 9:1"/>What is wise {is like a woman who} has built her own {spacious} house and made seven pillars to support its roof.<verse eid="PRO 9:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 9:2"/>{What is wise is like} a woman {who has prepared a meal for guests. She} has prepared the meat {to eat} and wine {to drink}. She has {fully} prepared her table for a meal.<verse eid="PRO 9:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 9:3"/>{What is wise is like} a woman who sends out her maids {to invite her dinner guests}. {What is wise is like} a woman who cries out at the highest place in the city {where everyone can hear her}.<verse eid="PRO 9:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 9:4"/>She tells those who are not wise, “Come into {my house}, all you naive people!<verse eid="PRO 9:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 9:5"/>Come {to me}! Eat the food that I have prepared, and drink the wine that I have prepared.<verse eid="PRO 9:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 9:6"/>Stop acting naively so that you can live {for a long time}. Do what will cause you to learn what you should understand.<verse eid="PRO 9:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 9:7"/>If you {try to} teach someone who ridicules {other people}, that person will ridicule you. If you correct an evil person, that person will hurt you.<verse eid="PRO 9:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 9:8"/>{So} do not correct a person who ridicules {other people}. If you do so, then that person will hate you. {However,} if you correct a wise person, that person will love you {for doing so}.<verse eid="PRO 9:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 9:9"/>If you instruct a wise person, then that person will become even wiser. If you teach a righteous person, then that person will learn even more.<verse eid="PRO 9:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 9:10"/>Reverently fearing Yahweh is necessary for being wise, and knowing what is holy is what you should understand.<verse eid="PRO 9:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 9:11"/>Surely being wise will cause you to live for many days, and it will cause you to live for many years.<verse eid="PRO 9:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 9:12"/>Any wise person benefits from being wise. But anyone who ridicules {other people} will suffer alone for doing so.”<verse eid="PRO 9:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 9:13"/>Foolish women speak loudly, act naively, and are very ignorant.<verse eid="PRO 9:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 9:14"/>They sit at the doors of the places where they dwell. {They sit} on seats at the highest place in the city {where everyone can hear them}.<verse eid="PRO 9:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 9:15"/>{They sit there} in order to cry out to the people who are walking past them. {They cry out to} those walking down the road, who are only concerned about where they are going.<verse eid="PRO 9:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 9:16"/>They tell those who are not wise, “Come into {my house}, all you naive people!<verse eid="PRO 9:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 9:17"/>{Come to me, because having sex with someone to whom you are not married is} as sweet as water that you have stolen. Indeed, {it is} as delicious as food that you eat all by yourself.”<verse eid="PRO 9:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 9:18"/>But men who go to the houses of such women are not aware that the men who have gone there before have died. {They are not aware} that the guests of such women are now in the deepest parts of the place where dead people are.<verse eid="PRO 9:18"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 9"/>
<chapter number="10" style="c" sid="PRO 10"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 10:1"/>{These are} the wise sayings {said} by Solomon: Wise children make their fathers glad, but foolish children make their mothers sad.<verse eid="PRO 10:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 10:2"/>Riches that people acquire by acting wickedly will not benefit them, but people who act righteously prevent themselves from dying {too soon}.<verse eid="PRO 10:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 10:3"/>Yahweh prevents righteous people from starving, but he prevents wicked people from getting what they want.<verse eid="PRO 10:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 10:4"/>People who are too lazy to work become poor, but people who work hard become rich.<verse eid="PRO 10:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 10:5"/>Sons who collect crops at the right time are insightful, but sons who sleep during the time to harvest crops are shameful.<verse eid="PRO 10:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 10:6"/>God blesses righteous people; but what wicked people say prevents others from knowing about the violent acts {that they do}.<verse eid="PRO 10:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 10:7"/>People will be happy when they remember righteous people, but people will forget wicked people as if they were something that decays {and disappears}.<verse eid="PRO 10:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 10:8"/>People who think wisely obey what people command {them to do that is good}, but people who speak foolishly destroy themselves.<verse eid="PRO 10:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 10:9"/>People who behave honestly will live safely; but God will catch people who behave deceitfully.<verse eid="PRO 10:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 10:10"/>People who gesture with their eyes {to deceive people} hurt {people}, and people who speak foolishly destroy themselves.<verse eid="PRO 10:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 10:11"/>What righteous people say is like a spring that enables people to live for a long time; but what wicked people say prevents others from knowing about the violent acts {that they do}.<verse eid="PRO 10:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 10:12"/>When people are hateful, they cause people to argue; but when people are loving, they forgive people who wrong them.<verse eid="PRO 10:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 10:13"/>Discerning people say what is wise, but someone must punish people who do not think wisely.<verse eid="PRO 10:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 10:14"/>Wise people sincerely consider what they should know, but people who speak foolishly are destructive.<verse eid="PRO 10:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 10:15"/>What rich people own keeps them safe like a wall keeps a city safe, but being poor destroys poor people.<verse eid="PRO 10:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 10:16"/>God rewards righteous people by allowing them to live {for a long time}, but God recompenses wicked people by punishing them for sinning.<verse eid="PRO 10:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 10:17"/>People who heed what is instructive will live for a long time; but people who do not let others correct them do what will destroy them.<verse eid="PRO 10:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 10:18"/>People who do not admit that they hate someone speak falsely. People who slander others are foolish.<verse eid="PRO 10:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 10:19"/>People who talk a lot sin a lot; but people who refrain from speaking {unnecessarily} are wise.<verse eid="PRO 10:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 10:20"/>What righteous people say is {as valuable as} the best silver; {but} what wicked people think is worthless.<verse eid="PRO 10:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 10:21"/>What righteous people say benefits many people, but foolish people die because they do not think wisely.<verse eid="PRO 10:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 10:22"/>When people become wealthy, {it is because} Yahweh has blessed them, and he does not make them suffer for it.<verse eid="PRO 10:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 10:23"/>Foolish people enjoy doing the wicked things that they planned {to do}, but understanding people enjoy what is wise.<verse eid="PRO 10:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 10:24"/>Wicked people will experience what frightens them; but righteous people will receive what they want.<verse eid="PRO 10:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 10:25"/>When something disastrous happens, it destroys wicked people, but righteous people are {like} a foundation that lasts forever.<verse eid="PRO 10:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 10:26"/>Lazy people irritate people who send them {to do something for them}, like vinegar irritates teeth and smoke irritates eyes.<verse eid="PRO 10:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 10:27"/>Reverently fearing Yahweh will cause a person to live for a long time, but wicked people will not live for a long time.<verse eid="PRO 10:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 10:28"/>What righteous people hope for leads to being joyful, but what wicked people hope for will not happen.<verse eid="PRO 10:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 10:29"/>What Yahweh does protects honest people like a fortress, but what he does destroys people who act sinfully.<verse eid="PRO 10:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 10:30"/>Righteous people will always be safe, but wicked people will never live in our land.<verse eid="PRO 10:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 10:31"/>Righteous people say what is wise, but Yahweh will stop people who speak perversely from speaking.<verse eid="PRO 10:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 10:32"/>What righteous people say is favorable, but what wicked people say is perverse.<verse eid="PRO 10:32"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 10"/>
<chapter number="11" style="c" sid="PRO 11"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 11:1"/>Yahweh detests {people} using weighing instruments in order to deceive others, but people who use correct weights {on their weighing instruments} please him.<verse eid="PRO 11:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 11:2"/>When people act proudly, they will soon disgrace themselves, but humble people are wise.<verse eid="PRO 11:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 11:3"/>Being honest will cause people who act uprightly to know what they should do, but  being deceitful will ruin people who act treacherously.<verse eid="PRO 11:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 11:4"/>What people own will not help them when Yahweh judges {the world}, but acting righteously will prevent people from dying.<verse eid="PRO 11:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 11:5"/>Being righteous will cause people whom Yahweh does not blame {for acting wickedly} to know what they should do, but being wicked will ruin those who act wickedly.<verse eid="PRO 11:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 11:6"/>Being righteous will cause people who act uprightly to escape, but what people who act treacherously want will cause someone to trap them.<verse eid="PRO 11:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 11:7"/>When wicked people die, what they hoped for never happens, what people who rely on how strong they are hoped for also never happens.<verse eid="PRO 11:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 11:8"/>Yahweh prevents righteous people from becoming distressed; but wicked people will become distressed instead.<verse eid="PRO 11:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 11:9"/>What people who reject God say ruins people they know, but what righteous people know will cause them to escape.<verse eid="PRO 11:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 11:10"/>People in a city rejoice when the righteous people {there} prosper, and they shout joyously when wicked people die.<verse eid="PRO 11:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 11:11"/>A city becomes great when people who act uprightly bless {the people there}, but what people who act wickedly say destroys that city.<verse eid="PRO 11:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 11:12"/>People who {openly} detest someone they know are not thinking wisely; but understanding people say nothing.<verse eid="PRO 11:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 11:13"/>People who gossip walk around telling {others} what is secret, but trustworthy people will not do so.<verse eid="PRO 11:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 11:14"/>Not having anyone to guide a people group will ruin that group, but having many people advise {a people group} will rescue {that group}.<verse eid="PRO 11:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 11:15"/>People who guarantee to pay a loan for someone they do not know will surely suffer, but people who hate agreeing to pay a loan for someone will be safe.<verse eid="PRO 11:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 11:16"/>People honor a gracious woman, but cruel people {only} gain wealth.<verse eid="PRO 11:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 11:17"/>People who are faithfully kind benefit themselves, but cruel people hurt themselves.<verse eid="PRO 11:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 11:18"/>People who act wickedly do not really gain anything, but God truly rewards people who do what is righteous.<verse eid="PRO 11:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 11:19"/>People who truly act righteously will live {for a long time}, but people who eagerly do what is evil will die.<verse eid="PRO 11:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 11:20"/>Yahweh detests people who think deceitfully, but people who act blamelessly please him.<verse eid="PRO 11:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 11:21"/>Yahweh will certainly punish wicked people. but he will not punish the offspring of righteous people.<verse eid="PRO 11:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 11:22"/>Attractive women who refuse to act discreetly are {as ridiculous as} a gold ring in a pig’s snout.<verse eid="PRO 11:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 11:23"/>What righteous people want only results in what is good, but what wicked people hope for results in {Yahweh} being angry.<verse eid="PRO 11:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 11:24"/>People who generously share {what they have with others} will receive even more, but people who keep more {of what they have} than they should keep will only lose it.<verse eid="PRO 11:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 11:25"/>People who generously bless others will prosper; and people who generously give others something to drink will also receive something to drink.<verse eid="PRO 11:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 11:26"/>People will curse people who {selfishly} hoard food {instead of selling it}, but they will bless people who sell it {when others need it}.<verse eid="PRO 11:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 11:27"/>Yahweh and others approve of people who earnestly try to do what is good, but evil things happen to people who try to do what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 11:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 11:28"/>People who depend on their money are those who will ruin themselves, but righteous people will thrive like a green plant.<verse eid="PRO 11:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 11:29"/>People who trouble their families will not inherit anything, and people who act foolishly will serve people who think wisely.<verse eid="PRO 11:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 11:30"/>What righteous people do is {like} a tree {with fruit} that keeps people alive, and people who persuade others are wise.<verse eid="PRO 11:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 11:31"/>Pay attention! Righteous people on the earth will get what they deserve; but even more so, wicked people and sinful people will {also} get what they deserve!<verse eid="PRO 11:31"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 11"/>
<chapter number="12" style="c" sid="PRO 12"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 12:1"/>People who love other people correcting them {also} love {learning} what they should know. But people who hate other people correcting them are foolish.<verse eid="PRO 12:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 12:2"/>Yahweh approves of people who are good, but he condemns people who plan to do what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 12:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 12:3"/>People cannot live stably by acting wickedly, but righteous people are {as stable as} a tree with immovable roots.<verse eid="PRO 12:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 12:4"/>A virtuous wife causes people to praise her husband, but a disgraceful wife {destroys her husband} like a disease that destroys his bones.<verse eid="PRO 12:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 12:5"/>What righteous people plan is just, {but} what wicked people advise is deceitful.<verse eid="PRO 12:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 12:6"/>What wicked people say {causes people to die like} someone who hides in wait in order to kill someone {who walks by}; but what upright people say will enable them to escape.<verse eid="PRO 12:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 12:7"/>Yahweh destroys wicked people and they will cease to exist, but the families of righteous people will continue to exist.<verse eid="PRO 12:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 12:8"/>People will praise someone according to how insightful that person is, but people will despise someone who thinks perversely.<verse eid="PRO 12:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 12:9"/>People whom others disrespect yet have servants are better than people who think they are important yet have no food.<verse eid="PRO 12:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 12:10"/>Righteous people take care of their animals, but even when wicked people {try to} act compassionately, they act cruelly.<verse eid="PRO 12:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 12:11"/>People who work hard will have enough food {to eat}, but people who waste time doing worthless things do not think wisely.<verse eid="PRO 12:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 12:12"/>Wicked people want what evil people steal, but righteous people benefit {others} like a tree with deep roots.<verse eid="PRO 12:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 12:13"/>What wicked people sinfully say will destroy them, but righteous people will not become distressed.<verse eid="PRO 12:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 12:14"/>What people say will satisfy them with what is good; what people work hard to accomplish will benefit them.<verse eid="PRO 12:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 12:15"/>Foolish people think that what they are doing is {always} right; but wise people listen to what other people advise {them to do}.<verse eid="PRO 12:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 12:16"/>People know immediately when foolish people are angry; but clever people ignore it when someone disrespects them.<verse eid="PRO 12:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 12:17"/>People who easily speak truthfully speak righteously, but witnesses who speak falsely speak deceitfully.<verse eid="PRO 12:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 12:18"/>When people speak without thinking {about what to say}, they hurt others like someone who stabs people with a sword, but what wise people say helps people heal.<verse eid="PRO 12:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 12:19"/>What people say truthfully will last forever, but what people say falsely will {only} last for a moment.<verse eid="PRO 12:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 12:20"/>People who plan to act evilly think deceitfully, but people who advise others to act peacefully will be joyful.<verse eid="PRO 12:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 12:21"/>Bad things do not happen to righteous people, but wicked people will experience many bad things.<verse eid="PRO 12:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 12:22"/>Yahweh detests people who speak falsely, but people who act faithfully please him.<verse eid="PRO 12:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 12:23"/>Clever people conceal what they know, but foolish people shout out foolish things.<verse eid="PRO 12:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 12:24"/>People who work hard will reign {over others}, but lazy people will become slaves.<verse eid="PRO 12:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 12:25"/>When people worry, they feel sad, but when someone says what is good, those people feel happy.<verse eid="PRO 12:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 12:26"/>Righteous people will guide the people they know, but what wicked people do causes them to do what will destroy them.<verse eid="PRO 12:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 12:27"/>Lazy people do not even cook the animals that they catch, but people who work hard acquire valuable riches.<verse eid="PRO 12:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 12:28"/>People who do what is righteous will live {for a long time}. Indeed, people who do so will not die {too soon}.<verse eid="PRO 12:28"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 12"/>
<chapter number="13" style="c" sid="PRO 13"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 13:1"/>Wise children pay attention when their fathers instruct them, but people who ridicule {other people} do not pay attention when people correct {them}.<verse eid="PRO 13:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 13:2"/>What people say will enable them to eat good {food}, but people who act treacherously {only} want to act violently.<verse eid="PRO 13:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 13:3"/>People who are careful about what they say enable themselves to stay alive, {but} people who speak carelessly destroy themselves.<verse eid="PRO 13:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 13:4"/>Lazy people always want something but never receive it, but people who work hard will receive more than what they want.<verse eid="PRO 13:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 13:5"/>Righteous people detest speaking falsely, but wicked people are disgusting and disgraceful.<verse eid="PRO 13:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 13:6"/>Acting righteously enables people who act blamelessly to be safe, but acting wickedly causes sinful people to do what will destroy them.<verse eid="PRO 13:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 13:7"/>Some people act as if they are wealthy while they are {actually} poor. Other people act as if they are poor while they are {actually} wealthy.<verse eid="PRO 13:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 13:8"/>Rich people {might} have to pay money {to someone who threatens them} in order to stay alive, but poor people do not {even} listen when someone threatens them.<verse eid="PRO 13:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 13:9"/>Righteous people live joyfully like a light {that shines brightly}, but wicked people {will merely die} like an oil lamp that stops burning {oil}.<verse eid="PRO 13:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 13:10"/>People acting proudly only causes people to argue, but people who let others advise them are wise.<verse eid="PRO 13:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 13:11"/>Riches that people gain effortlessly will diminish, but people who gain riches by working hard will increase {their riches}.<verse eid="PRO 13:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 13:12"/>People despair when they do not receive what they hope to receive, but receiving what people want to receive is {like} a tree {with fruit} that keeps those people alive.<verse eid="PRO 13:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 13:13"/>People who detest what others {try to} teach them will suffer for doing so, but God will reward those very people who reverently fear what he has commanded.<verse eid="PRO 13:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 13:14"/>What wise people teach is like a spring that enables people to live for a long time. It enables people to avoid what could kill them.<verse eid="PRO 13:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 13:15"/>People approve of people who are very insightful, but how treacherous people live is harsh.<verse eid="PRO 13:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 13:16"/>All clever people act according to what they know, but foolish people show how foolish they are {by how they act}.<verse eid="PRO 13:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 13:17"/>Bad things happen to messengers who are not reliable, but reliable messengers help people heal.<verse eid="PRO 13:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 13:18"/>People who do not let other people correct them will be poor and ashamed, but people will respect those people who let other people rebuke them.<verse eid="PRO 13:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 13:19"/>People feel pleasant when they get what they want, but foolish people detest refusing to do what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 13:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 13:20"/>People who associate with wise people will become wise {themselves}, but people who are companions of foolish people will agonize.<verse eid="PRO 13:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 13:21"/>Bad things happen to sinful people, but good things happen to righteous people.<verse eid="PRO 13:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 13:22"/>Good people will leave riches for their grandchildren when they die, but righteous people will receive the riches that sinful people have saved.<verse eid="PRO 13:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 13:23"/>Poor people have fields that can produce a lot of food, but unjust people take it all away {from them}.<verse eid="PRO 13:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 13:24"/>Parents who do not physically punish {their children act as if they} hate their children, but parents who {truly} love their children are careful to discipline them.<verse eid="PRO 13:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 13:25"/>Righteous people eat enough {food} to satisfy themselves, but wicked people are always hungry.<verse eid="PRO 13:25"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 13"/>
<chapter number="14" style="c" sid="PRO 14"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 14:1"/>The wisest women help their families thrive, but foolish women ruin their families by what they do.<verse eid="PRO 14:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 14:2"/>People who behave uprightly reverently fear Yahweh, but people who behave deceptively detest Yahweh.<verse eid="PRO 14:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 14:3"/>What foolish people say causes someone to punish them for being proud, but what wise people say keeps them alive.<verse eid="PRO 14:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 14:4"/>Where there are not any oxen {to feed in the barn}, the feeding container is clean; but oxen work to produce a lot of crops.<verse eid="PRO 14:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 14:5"/>Honest witnesses do not lie, but dishonest witnesses lie easily.<verse eid="PRO 14:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 14:6"/>People who ridicule {other people} try to become wise and fail to do so, but understanding people can easily learn what they should know.<verse eid="PRO 14:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 14:7"/>Stay away from foolish people because you will not learn anything from what they say.<verse eid="PRO 14:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 14:8"/>Clever people know what to do because they are wise, but foolish people deceive themselves because they are foolish.<verse eid="PRO 14:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 14:9"/>Foolish people scorn making amends with Yahweh after sinning, but Yahweh approves of upright people.<verse eid="PRO 14:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 14:10"/>Only miserable people know how miserable they are, and joyful people cannot share what they feel with someone they do not know.<verse eid="PRO 14:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 14:11"/>The families of wicked people will die out, but the families of upright people will thrive.<verse eid="PRO 14:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 14:12"/>People think they know the right way to behave, but people who behave that way will ultimately die.<verse eid="PRO 14:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 14:13"/>People who are laughing may still be suffering, and people who feel joyful may ultimately feel sad.<verse eid="PRO 14:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 14:14"/>People who refuse {to live righteously} will receive from Yahweh what they deserve; and good people {will also receive from Yahweh} what they deserve.<verse eid="PRO 14:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 14:15"/>Naive people believe whatever people say, but clever people think carefully about what they do.<verse eid="PRO 14:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 14:16"/>Wise people are afraid of {doing what is evil} and refuse to do what is evil, but foolish people make themselves angry and are overconfident.<verse eid="PRO 14:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 14:17"/>People who quickly become angry act foolishly, and people hate people who plan to do what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 14:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 14:18"/>Naive people will act foolishly, but clever people will learn what they should know.<verse eid="PRO 14:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 14:19"/>Evil people will {respectfully} bow in front of good people, and wicked people will bow at the doors {of the houses} where righteous people {dwell}.<verse eid="PRO 14:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 14:20"/>Even the people whom poor people know hate them, but many people love rich people.<verse eid="PRO 14:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 14:21"/>Sinful people scorn the people they know, but people who are kind to suffering people are happy.<verse eid="PRO 14:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 14:22"/>People who plan to act evilly surely act deceptively, but people are faithful and trustworthy to people who plan to do what is good.<verse eid="PRO 14:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 14:23"/>Whenever people work hard, they will earn money, but when people {only} talk, they will only remain poor.<verse eid="PRO 14:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 14:24"/>Wise people will acquire wealth, but foolish people {only} act more foolishly because they are foolish.<verse eid="PRO 14:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 14:25"/>Truthful witnesses save people from dying, but people who lie easily are deceptive.<verse eid="PRO 14:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 14:26"/>Strong people are confident because they reverently fear Yahweh. Those people will protect their children.<verse eid="PRO 14:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 14:27"/>Reverently fearing Yahweh is like a spring that enables people to live for a long time. It enables people to avoid what could kill them.<verse eid="PRO 14:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 14:28"/>Kings who rule over many people are glorious, but rulers who have no people {to rule over} have nothing.<verse eid="PRO 14:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 14:29"/>People who do not become angry quickly understand a lot, but people who become angry quickly show everyone how foolish they are.<verse eid="PRO 14:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 14:30"/>Feeling peaceful makes a person’s body healthy, but envying others {makes a person’s body unhealthy, like something that} rots a person’s bones.<verse eid="PRO 14:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 14:31"/>People who make poor people suffer despise Yahweh, who made them, but people who are kind to needy people respect Yahweh.<verse eid="PRO 14:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 14:32"/>Wicked people destroy themselves by doing evil things, but righteous people feel safe {even} when they die.<verse eid="PRO 14:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 14:33"/>Understanding people think wisely, and even foolish people know about what is wise.<verse eid="PRO 14:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="PRO 14:34"/>Acting righteously makes a country great, but acting sinfully disgraces a people group.<verse eid="PRO 14:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="PRO 14:35"/>Insightful servants please their kings, but kings are furious with disgraceful people.<verse eid="PRO 14:35"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 14"/>
<chapter number="15" style="c" sid="PRO 15"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 15:1"/>Replying gently to angry people will calm them, but speaking harshly {to them} will make them angrier.<verse eid="PRO 15:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 15:2"/>What wise people say makes others appreciate what they should know, but foolish people constantly say what is foolish.<verse eid="PRO 15:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 15:3"/>Yahweh sees everything that is happening; he observes both evil people and good people.<verse eid="PRO 15:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 15:4"/>What people say soothingly is {like} a tree {with fruit} that keeps people alive, but what people say deceitfully makes people despair.<verse eid="PRO 15:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 15:5"/>Foolish people detest what their fathers say to correct them, but people who let others rebuke them are clever.<verse eid="PRO 15:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 15:6"/>Righteous people have houses that contain a lot of riches, but what wicked people gain troubles them.<verse eid="PRO 15:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 15:7"/>What wise people say informs others of what they should know, but what foolish people think does not do that.<verse eid="PRO 15:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 15:8"/>Yahweh detests what wicked people offer {to him}, but what upright people pray pleases him.<verse eid="PRO 15:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 15:9"/>Yahweh detests what wicked people do, but he loves people who diligently try to act righteously.<verse eid="PRO 15:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 15:10"/>Yahweh will severely punish people who refuse to live righteously, {and} people who hate other people correcting them will perish.<verse eid="PRO 15:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 15:11"/>Yahweh knows everything about the place where dead people are, so he surely knows everything that everyone thinks!<verse eid="PRO 15:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 15:12"/>People who ridicule others despise anyone who corrects them; they avoid wise people.<verse eid="PRO 15:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 15:13"/>People smile when they are happy, but feeling sad can make people despair.<verse eid="PRO 15:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 15:14"/>Understanding people try to learn what they should know, but foolish people satisfy themselves with what is foolish.<verse eid="PRO 15:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 15:15"/>What happens every day that suffering people live makes them wretched, but cheerful people live like people who are always feasting.<verse eid="PRO 15:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 15:16"/>It is better for someone to have a few things while reverently fearing Yahweh than for someone to have a lot of riches while worrying.<verse eid="PRO 15:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 15:17"/>It is better for someone to have a small meal where people love each other than to have a large meal where people hate each other.<verse eid="PRO 15:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 15:18"/>People who easily become angry cause people to argue, but people who do not become angry quickly will stop people from arguing.<verse eid="PRO 15:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 15:19"/>Lazy people live unproductively like {people that have} a thorny plant {blocking their paths}, but upright people live productively {like people who are walking on} a road that is easy to walk on.<verse eid="PRO 15:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 15:20"/>Wise children make their fathers happy, but foolish children detest their mothers.<verse eid="PRO 15:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 15:21"/>People who are not wise enjoy acting foolishly, but understanding people act rightly.<verse eid="PRO 15:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 15:22"/>What people plan fails when no one advises them, but what people plan succeeds when many people advise them.<verse eid="PRO 15:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 15:23"/>People rejoice when they answer someone aptly. It is so good to say something at the right time!<verse eid="PRO 15:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 15:24"/>How insightful people live causes them to live for a long time in order for them to avoid going to the place where dead people are.<verse eid="PRO 15:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 15:25"/>Yahweh will destroy what proud people own, but he protects the {few} things that widows own.<verse eid="PRO 15:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 15:26"/>Yahweh detests the evil things that people think, but the pleasing things that people say are pure.<verse eid="PRO 15:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 15:27"/>People who gain wealth in an unjust manner trouble their families, but people who refuse bribes will live {for a long time}.<verse eid="PRO 15:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 15:28"/>Righteous people think carefully about how to reply to people, but wicked people constantly say what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 15:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 15:29"/>Yahweh does not listen to wicked people, but he listens to what righteous people pray.<verse eid="PRO 15:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 15:30"/>People feel happy when they see someone smile, {and} people feel healthy when they hear something good.<verse eid="PRO 15:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 15:31"/>People who listen when others rebuke them in a way that will keep them alive will become wise.<verse eid="PRO 15:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 15:32"/>People who refuse to let others correct them {act as if they} despise themselves, but people who listen when others rebuke them think wisely.<verse eid="PRO 15:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 15:33"/>Reverently fearing Yahweh makes people wise, and people must be humble before other people respect them.<verse eid="PRO 15:33"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 15"/>
<chapter number="16" style="c" sid="PRO 16"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 16:1"/>People plan what they want {to say}, but Yahweh determines how they will reply.<verse eid="PRO 16:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 16:2"/>People think that everything they do is right, but Yahweh {rightly} evaluates what they think.<verse eid="PRO 16:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 16:3"/>Entrust what you do to Yahweh, and he will make what you plan {to do} succeed.<verse eid="PRO 16:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 16:4"/>When Yahweh made everything, he planned what would happen to each thing. He has even made wicked people for the time when he will punish them.<verse eid="PRO 16:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 16:5"/>Yahweh detests all proud people; he will certainly punish them.<verse eid="PRO 16:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 16:6"/>People can atone for acting sinfully by being faithful and trustworthy. People who reverently fear Yahweh will avoid doing what is evil.<verse eid="PRO 16:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 16:7"/>When Yahweh likes what people do, he even causes their enemies to be peaceful with them.<verse eid="PRO 16:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 16:8"/>It is better {for someone} to have a few things while being righteous, than {for someone} to have a lot of crops while being unjust.<verse eid="PRO 16:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 16:9"/>People plan what they want to do, but Yahweh determines what they will {actually} do.<verse eid="PRO 16:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 16:10"/>{Ideally,} what kings say is from God, {and} when kings judge, they surely speak justly.<verse eid="PRO 16:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 16:11"/>Yahweh made weighing instruments {for us} to use honestly. Indeed, he made all the stones people carry in bags to use for weighing things.<verse eid="PRO 16:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 16:12"/>{Ideally,} kings detest people acting wickedly because acting righteously causes kings to rule securely.<verse eid="PRO 16:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 16:13"/>{Ideally,} kings enjoy when people speak righteously. Indeed, they love people who speak uprightly.<verse eid="PRO 16:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 16:14"/>When kings are angry, they cause people to die, so wise people will appease them.<verse eid="PRO 16:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 16:15"/>When kings are happy, they let people live; when they approve of people, it is as refreshing as rain in springtime.<verse eid="PRO 16:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 16:16"/>Becoming wise is better than having gold. Indeed, it is better to choose to become understanding than to have silver.<verse eid="PRO 16:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 16:17"/>Upright people act in a way that avoids doing what is evil; people who want to stay alive are careful about what they do.<verse eid="PRO 16:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 16:18"/>If people are proud, then something will destroy them. Indeed, if people are arrogant, then something will ruin them.<verse eid="PRO 16:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 16:19"/>It is better to live humbly among poor people than to {live proudly and} receive some of what proud people have taken from others.<verse eid="PRO 16:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 16:20"/>People who act prudently in a matter will succeed, and people who trust in Yahweh are happy.<verse eid="PRO 16:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 16:21"/>People will call those who think wisely, “understanding ones,” and pleasant things that people say cause others to learn.<verse eid="PRO 16:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 16:22"/>Being insightful is {like} a spring that enables insightful people to live for a long time, but being foolish results in other people punishing foolish people.<verse eid="PRO 16:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 16:23"/>What wise people think causes them to speak insightfully, and what those people say causes others to learn.<verse eid="PRO 16:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 16:24"/>The pleasing things that people say are {like} a honeycomb: They cause people to feel pleasant and healthy.<verse eid="PRO 16:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 16:25"/>People think they know the right way to behave, but people who behave that way will ultimately die.<verse eid="PRO 16:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 16:26"/>Being hungry helps working people work because wanting to eat motivates people to keep on working.<verse eid="PRO 16:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 16:27"/>Worthless people plot how to hurt others; the evil things they say harm others like fire burns {people}.<verse eid="PRO 16:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 16:28"/>Perverse people cause other people to argue with each other, and people who gossip about others cause friends to stop being friends.<verse eid="PRO 16:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 16:29"/>Violent people tempt people whom they know {to sin}, and they guide them to behave wickedly.<verse eid="PRO 16:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 16:30"/>People who use their eyes to signal to others are planning to do something perverse; people who use their lips to signal to others are about to do the evil thing {that they had planned to do}.<verse eid="PRO 16:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 16:31"/>Living for a long time is {honorable, like} a magnificent crown {on someone’s head}; people are able to live for a long time by living righteously.<verse eid="PRO 16:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 16:32"/>It is better to be someone who does not become angry quickly than to be powerful. It is better to control oneself than to be {as powerful as} someone who conquers a city.<verse eid="PRO 16:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 16:33"/>People throw lots {in order to decide what to do}, but Yahweh decides whatever happens.<verse eid="PRO 16:33"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 16"/>
<chapter number="17" style="c" sid="PRO 17"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 17:1"/>It is better for someone to have a little stale food {to eat} while living peacefully than for someone to live in a house where people frequently eat large meals while arguing with each other.<verse eid="PRO 17:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 17:2"/>An insightful slave will rule over his master’s disgraceful son. People will consider that slave to be one of his master’s sons, and he will inherit some of what his master’s sons inherit.<verse eid="PRO 17:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 17:3"/>People use crucibles and furnaces to test and refine silver and gold. Yahweh tests what people are thinking in a similar manner.<verse eid="PRO 17:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 17:4"/>People who act evilly listen carefully when people speak what is sinful; people who lie pay attention when people speak what destroys {others}.<verse eid="PRO 17:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 17:5"/>People who ridicule poor people despise Yahweh, who made them; Yahweh will certainly punish people who rejoice when other people experience disastrous things.<verse eid="PRO 17:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 17:6"/>Old people are proud of their grandchildren, and children are proud of their parents.<verse eid="PRO 17:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 17:7"/>It is not fitting for worthless people to speak eloquently. It is even less fitting for royal officials to speak falsely!<verse eid="PRO 17:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 17:8"/>People who pay bribes think that bribes are magical; {they think that} everything they do will be successful.<verse eid="PRO 17:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 17:9"/>People who want to love forgive people who wrong them, but people who repeatedly mention how someone wronged them cause friends to stop being friends.<verse eid="PRO 17:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 17:10"/>Rebuking causes understanding people to learn more than beating foolish people a hundred times {with a stick causes them to learn}.<verse eid="PRO 17:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 17:11"/>Evil people only want to rebel, so a merciless messenger will come and punish them.<verse eid="PRO 17:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 17:12"/>It would be better to meet a female bear that is furious because someone stole her cubs than to meet foolish people while they are acting foolishly!<verse eid="PRO 17:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 17:13"/>If people react to experiencing what is good by doing what is evil, then what is evil will continually affect their families.<verse eid="PRO 17:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 17:14"/>When people start arguing with each other, it is as difficult to stop as it is to stop water that is leaking out of something, so prevent yourself from arguing before you start to argue.<verse eid="PRO 17:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 17:15"/>There are people who acquit guilty people, and there are people who condemn innocent people; Yahweh detests both types of people.<verse eid="PRO 17:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 17:16"/>How useless it is for foolish people to try to pay money in order to become wise when they are unable to think!<verse eid="PRO 17:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 17:17"/>A friend loves {you} all the time, and relatives exist in order to help {other relatives} when disastrous things happen.<verse eid="PRO 17:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 17:18"/>People who do not think wisely agree to pay someone else’s loan and even guarantee to pay that loan in front of people whom they know.<verse eid="PRO 17:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 17:19"/>People who love to sin {also} love to cause people to argue; people who brag a lot cause others to destroy them.<verse eid="PRO 17:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 17:20"/>People who think deceitfully will never experience any good things, and bad things will happen to people who speak deceitfully.<verse eid="PRO 17:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 17:21"/>Foolish people grieve their parents. Indeed, worthless people will not cause their fathers to be joyful.<verse eid="PRO 17:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 17:22"/>People who feel happy will heal, but depressed people will be unhealthy.<verse eid="PRO 17:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 17:23"/>People secretly bribe wicked judges so that they judge unjustly.<verse eid="PRO 17:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 17:24"/>Understanding people concentrate on what is wise, but foolish people cannot concentrate on anything.<verse eid="PRO 17:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 17:25"/>Foolish children grieve their fathers and make their mothers miserable.<verse eid="PRO 17:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 17:26"/>Punishing innocent people is surely wrong, {and} beating royal officials is {also} wrong.<verse eid="PRO 17:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 17:27"/>People who refrain from speaking {unnecessarily} are knowledgeable, and people who remain calm are understanding people.<verse eid="PRO 17:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 17:28"/>People will think even foolish people are wise if those foolish people do not speak. Indeed, people who refrain from speaking are understanding people.<verse eid="PRO 17:28"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 17"/>
<chapter number="18" style="c" sid="PRO 18"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 18:1"/>People who avoid other people only care about doing what they want to do. They refuse to do anything that is wise.<verse eid="PRO 18:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 18:2"/>Foolish people hate {learning} what they should understand. Instead, they only like to tell others what they think.<verse eid="PRO 18:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 18:3"/>People treat wicked people contemptuously, and people scold people who act shamefully.<verse eid="PRO 18:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 18:4"/>What wise people say is as profound as a deep ocean. {Wise people are like} a fountain or brook that flows abundantly with what is wise.<verse eid="PRO 18:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 18:5"/>It is very evil {for judges} to favor guilty people in order to prevent judging innocent people justly.<verse eid="PRO 18:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 18:6"/>What foolish people say makes people argue, and it makes people want to beat them.<verse eid="PRO 18:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 18:7"/>What foolish people say will ruin them. Indeed, what they say will trouble them like a trap {troubles an animal}.<verse eid="PRO 18:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 18:8"/>People are eager to listen to what people who gossip say, and what they say deeply affects those who hear it.<verse eid="PRO 18:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 18:9"/>People who are lazy when they work are like people who destroy things.<verse eid="PRO 18:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 18:10"/>Yahweh is {like} a strong tower that righteous people run into and are safe.<verse eid="PRO 18:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 18:11"/>What rich people own keeps them safe like walls keep cities safe; they think what they own protects them as well as a high wall.<verse eid="PRO 18:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 18:12"/>If people think proudly, then something will destroy them; people must be humble before other people respect them.<verse eid="PRO 18:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 18:13"/>It is foolish and shameful for someone to reply to what a person has said before hearing it.<verse eid="PRO 18:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 18:14"/>How people feel can enable them to endure being sick. However, it is very difficult to make a depressed person feel better!<verse eid="PRO 18:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 18:15"/>Understanding people learn what they should know. Indeed, wise people try to learn what they should know.<verse eid="PRO 18:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 18:16"/>Giving something {to someone} can benefit the one who gives it; doing so can enable that person to meet important people.<verse eid="PRO 18:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 18:17"/>People who state their cases first seem to be right until people whom they know arrive and question them.<verse eid="PRO 18:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 18:18"/>Throwing lots {in order to decide something} can make people stop arguing, it can also decide who is right between powerful people.<verse eid="PRO 18:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 18:19"/>It is more difficult to reconcile with a relative {whom you have} offended than {to conquer} a fortified city; and when people argue, they avoid each other as if a castle’s strong gate were between them.<verse eid="PRO 18:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 18:20"/>What people say will satisfy them when they are hungry. Indeed, what people say will satisfy them.<verse eid="PRO 18:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 18:21"/>What people say can cause people to die or remain alive. And people who love to talk will experience the consequences {for what they say}.<verse eid="PRO 18:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 18:22"/>Men who marry get what is good and Yahweh approves of them.<verse eid="PRO 18:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 18:23"/>Poor people plead for others to be merciful {to them}, but rich people reply {to them} rudely.<verse eid="PRO 18:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 18:24"/>Having {unreliable} friends will destroy a person, but loving friends exist who are more loyal than brothers.<verse eid="PRO 18:24"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 18"/>
<chapter number="19" style="c" sid="PRO 19"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 19:1"/>It is better to be poor and behave honestly than to speak deceitfully and be foolish.<verse eid="PRO 19:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 19:2"/>Furthermore, it is very bad for people to not know {what they should know}; people sin who act hastily.<verse eid="PRO 19:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 19:3"/>People who act foolishly destroy themselves, yet they become furious with Yahweh {and blame him}.<verse eid="PRO 19:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 19:4"/>Wealthy people {easily} make many friends, but poor people lose {even} the friends they have.<verse eid="PRO 19:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 19:5"/>Someone will surely punish lying witnesses. Indeed, someone will surely punish people who lie easily.<verse eid="PRO 19:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 19:6"/>A lot of people want royal officials to favor them, and {it seems like} everyone wants to be friends with generous people.<verse eid="PRO 19:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 19:7"/>All the relatives of poor people despise them, and even their friends avoid them! Although they call out {to them for help}, they do not {respond}.<verse eid="PRO 19:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 19:8"/>People who think wisely benefit themselves; people who remember what they should understand will surely succeed.<verse eid="PRO 19:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 19:9"/>Someone will surely punish lying witnesses. Indeed, people who lie easily will die.<verse eid="PRO 19:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 19:10"/>It is wrong for foolish people to live luxuriously, and it is even worse for slaves to reign over princes!<verse eid="PRO 19:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 19:11"/>Insightful people do not get angry quickly, and people show how honorable they are by forgiving {people who} sin {against them}.<verse eid="PRO 19:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 19:12"/>When kings are furious, they frighten people like the roaring of young lions {frightens people}, but when they approve of people, it is as refreshing as dew on plants.<verse eid="PRO 19:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 19:13"/>Foolish children destroy their fathers, and when wives argue {with their husbands}, it is {as annoying as} constantly dripping water.<verse eid="PRO 19:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 19:14"/>People inherit houses and riches from their fathers, but Yahweh {alone} gives {men} insightful wives.<verse eid="PRO 19:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 19:15"/>Lazy people sleep well, but {such} idle people are {always} hungry.<verse eid="PRO 19:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 19:16"/>People who obey what others command them enable themselves to stay alive, but people who do not care about what they do will die.<verse eid="PRO 19:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 19:17"/>Being kind to poor people is {like} loaning money to Yahweh; he will reward anyone who does so.<verse eid="PRO 19:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 19:18"/>Correct your children while you still can; and do not allow yourself to kill them.<verse eid="PRO 19:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 19:19"/>Very angry people will pay {for being angry}; if you rescue them {from what they must pay}, you will have to do so again and again.<verse eid="PRO 19:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 19:20"/>Pay attention to what people advise you {to do} and let people teach you in order to become wise when you are about to die.<verse eid="PRO 19:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 19:21"/>People plan to do many things, but {only} what Yahweh advises will succeed.<verse eid="PRO 19:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 19:22"/>People want others to be faithful, and poor people are better than people who lie.<verse eid="PRO 19:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 19:23"/>Reverently fearing Yahweh causes people to live for a long time; such people rest contently, nothing will harm them.<verse eid="PRO 19:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 19:24"/>Lazy people put their hands in a dish {of food}, {but are so lazy that} they will not lift the food to their mouths.<verse eid="PRO 19:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 19:25"/>{If you} punish people who ridicule {others}, {then} naive people {who see you do that} will become sensible. {If you} correct understanding people, {then} they will learn what they should know.<verse eid="PRO 19:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 19:26"/>Children who act violently toward their fathers and chase away their mothers are disgraceful and embarrassing.<verse eid="PRO 19:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 19:27"/>My child, if you stop listening to what people teach you, then you will reject what you {already} know that people told you.<verse eid="PRO 19:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 19:28"/>Worthless witnesses scorn what is just, and wicked people enjoy acting sinfully as if they were gulping down delicious food.<verse eid="PRO 19:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 19:29"/>Yahweh is ready to condemn people who ridicule {others}, and he is ready to beat fools on their backs.<verse eid="PRO 19:29"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 19"/>
<chapter number="20" style="c" sid="PRO 20"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 20:1"/>People who drink too much of what can intoxicate them ridicule and fight others; all people who cannot walk properly because they drank too much of what can intoxicate them are very foolish.<verse eid="PRO 20:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 20:2"/>When kings are terrifyingly angry, they frighten people like the roaring of young lions {frightens people}; people who make kings angry cause themselves to die.<verse eid="PRO 20:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 20:3"/>It is honorable to cease arguing with other people, but all foolish people are eager to argue with others.<verse eid="PRO 20:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 20:4"/>Lazy farmers do not plow {their fields} when they should, so when it is time to harvest {crops}, they look {for crops in their fields}, but there are none.<verse eid="PRO 20:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 20:5"/>Discerning what people are thinking about advising {others} is {as difficult as} drawing water out of a deep {well}, but understanding people are able to do so.<verse eid="PRO 20:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 20:6"/>Many people claim to be faithful, but very few people act faithfully!<verse eid="PRO 20:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 20:7"/>Righteous people behave honestly; God will bless their children.<verse eid="PRO 20:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 20:8"/>{Ideally,} kings who sit on their thrones in order to judge {people} discern anything that is evil and remove it {from their lands}.<verse eid="PRO 20:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 20:9"/>No one can truthfully say, “I do not think sinfully anymore; I do not sin anymore.”<verse eid="PRO 20:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 20:10"/>Yahweh detests {people dishonestly using} differing weights and measurements {to benefit themselves}.<verse eid="PRO 20:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 20:11"/>Even young people show people {who they are} by what they do; how they act shows whether they are innocent and right.<verse eid="PRO 20:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 20:12"/>Yahweh has made both ears with which to hear and eyes with which to see.<verse eid="PRO 20:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 20:13"/>If you sleep a lot, you will become poor; {but} if you stay awake {and work}, you will have plenty of food.<verse eid="PRO 20:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 20:14"/>Buyers claim that something is not good at all {when they are bargaining with you about its price}. But {after they buy it,} they go and boast {to their friends about the good price they bought it for}.<verse eid="PRO 20:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 20:15"/>Gold and precious jewels are plentiful, but the knowledgeable things that people say are extremely precious.<verse eid="PRO 20:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 20:16"/>Take the coats of people who promise to pay a loan for someone whom they do not know. Indeed, hold onto the coats of people who do so for a foreigner.<verse eid="PRO 20:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 20:17"/>Food people get by deceiving {others} may taste sweet {to them}, but what eventually happens to them will be as unpleasant as having a mouth full of stones.<verse eid="PRO 20:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 20:18"/>What people plan succeeds when others advise them, so let others advise you before you start fighting a war.<verse eid="PRO 20:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 20:19"/>People who walk around gossiping tell {others} what is secret, so avoid people who speak carelessly.<verse eid="PRO 20:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 20:20"/>People who curse their parents {will die like} an oil lamp that stops burning {oil} in a totally dark place.<verse eid="PRO 20:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 20:21"/>What people inherit hastily before the proper time will ultimately not result in {Yahweh} blessing {them}.<verse eid="PRO 20:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 20:22"/>Do not say that you will harm someone who has harmed you. Rather, wait for Yahweh {to resolve the matter}, so that he may vindicate you.<verse eid="PRO 20:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 20:23"/>Yahweh detests {people dishonestly using} differing weights {to benefit themselves}. Indeed, {using} weighing instruments in order to deceive {others} is very bad.<verse eid="PRO 20:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 20:24"/>Yahweh directs what happens to powerful people. So then, people surely cannot comprehend what will happen to them!<verse eid="PRO 20:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 20:25"/>It is dangerous for people to declare thoughtlessly that something is holy to Yahweh, and then think about what they have done after they have done so.<verse eid="PRO 20:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 20:26"/>Wise kings remove wicked people {from their lands}, and {they punish them like farmers} crush grain under a threshing wheel.<verse eid="PRO 20:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 20:27"/>People’s spirits are {like} lamps that Yahweh has given them; they help people discern everything that deeply affects them.<verse eid="PRO 20:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 20:28"/>Being faithful and trustworthy makes kings safe. Indeed, being faithful enables them to rule securely.<verse eid="PRO 20:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 20:29"/>People admire young men because they are strong, but people admire old men because they are wise.<verse eid="PRO 20:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 20:30"/>Severely beating people may stop them from acting evilly, and hitting people {may change} what deeply affects them.<verse eid="PRO 20:30"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 20"/>
<chapter number="21" style="c" sid="PRO 21"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 21:1"/>Yahweh directs what kings think like {a farmer directs} streams to bring water anywhere he wants {it to go}.<verse eid="PRO 21:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 21:2"/>People think that everything they do is right, but Yahweh {rightly} evaluates what they think.<verse eid="PRO 21:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 21:3"/>Acting righteously and justly is more important to Yahweh than sacrificing animals {to him}.<verse eid="PRO 21:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 21:4"/>Being proud and arrogant guide what wicked people do like a lamp {shows people where to go}; they are sinful.<verse eid="PRO 21:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 21:5"/>What diligent people plan will certainly profit them, but all those who act too hastily will certainly become poor.<verse eid="PRO 21:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 21:6"/>When people gain wealth by speaking falsely, that wealth quickly vanishes like mist {and what they do} will kill them.<verse eid="PRO 21:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 21:7"/>When wicked people act violently, they destroy themselves because they refuse to act justly.<verse eid="PRO 21:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 21:8"/>Guilty people act perversely, but innocent people act uprightly.<verse eid="PRO 21:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 21:9"/>It is better to live {alone} in a corner of a housetop than to live inside a house with a wife who always argues {with you}.<verse eid="PRO 21:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 21:10"/>Wicked people strongly desire to act evilly, they will not be merciful to the people they know.<verse eid="PRO 21:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 21:11"/>If you punish people who ridicule others, {then} naive people {who see you do that} will become wise, and if you teach wise people, they will become {even more} knowledgeable.<verse eid="PRO 21:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 21:12"/>{Yahweh,} the Righteous One, knows the families of wicked people; he destroys them.<verse eid="PRO 21:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 21:13"/>People who refuse to listen to poor people when they cry out {for help} will also cry out {for help themselves}, but no one will help them.<verse eid="PRO 21:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 21:14"/>Secretly giving something to an angry person will stop them from being angry. Indeed, secretly bribing a furious person will calm them down.<verse eid="PRO 21:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 21:15"/>Righteous people enjoy acting justly, but acting justly terrifies people who act sinfully.<verse eid="PRO 21:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 21:16"/>People who stop behaving insightfully will end up in the place where the spirits of dead people are together.<verse eid="PRO 21:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 21:17"/>People who love what is pleasurable will be poor. Indeed, people who love {luxuries like} wine and olive oil will never be rich.<verse eid="PRO 21:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 21:18"/>Wicked people will suffer instead of righteous people, and treacherous people {will suffer} in place of upright people.<verse eid="PRO 21:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 21:19"/>It is better to live {alone} in a deserted land than {to live} with an argumentative and vexing wife.<verse eid="PRO 21:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 21:20"/>Wise people have precious riches and olive oil, but foolish people waste everything that they have.<verse eid="PRO 21:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 21:21"/>People who diligently try to be righteous and faithful will live {for a long time}, will be righteous, and people will respect them.<verse eid="PRO 21:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 21:22"/>Wise people conquer cities that mighty warriors are defending; they pull down the walls that people {in those cities} believe will protect them.<verse eid="PRO 21:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 21:23"/>People who are careful about anything they say avoid becoming distressed.<verse eid="PRO 21:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 21:24"/>People who ridicule others act presumptuously and arrogantly; they behave furiously and presumptuously.<verse eid="PRO 21:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 21:25"/>Lazy people want what will kill them because they refuse to work.<verse eid="PRO 21:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 21:26"/>Lazy people always want more things for themselves, but righteous people generously give {what they have to others}.<verse eid="PRO 21:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 21:27"/>What wicked people offer {to Yahweh} is detestable; it is even more {detestable} when they are offering something {to Yahweh} while intending to act wickedly!<verse eid="PRO 21:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 21:28"/>Witnesses who lie will die, but when people who listen carefully speak, others will always remember {what they said}.<verse eid="PRO 21:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 21:29"/>Wicked people show how stubborn they are, but upright people think about what they do.<verse eid="PRO 21:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 21:30"/>There is absolutely nothing that is wise, understanding, and advisable, but is {also} the opposite of what Yahweh wants.<verse eid="PRO 21:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 21:31"/>Soldiers prepare to fight, but Yahweh determines who wins {that fight}.<verse eid="PRO 21:31"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 21"/>
<chapter number="22" style="c" sid="PRO 22"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 22:1"/>Being someone whom people respect is more important than being very wealthy. Indeed, being someone whom others approve of is better than having silver and gold.<verse eid="PRO 22:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 22:2"/>Rich people and poor people have {at least} one thing in common: Yahweh made both of them.<verse eid="PRO 22:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 22:3"/>Sensible people observe something dangerous happening and avoid it, but naive people {ignorantly} do not avoid it and suffer {for doing so}.<verse eid="PRO 22:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 22:4"/>People who are humble, who reverently fear Yahweh, will become rich. People will respect them, and they will live {for a long time}.<verse eid="PRO 22:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 22:5"/>Deceptive people live {dangerously,} as if they were walking down a road covered with thorns and traps, {but} people who want to stay alive avoid living that way.<verse eid="PRO 22:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 22:6"/>Teach children how to behave {properly}, so that when they become old, they will still continue to do so.<verse eid="PRO 22:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 22:7"/>Rich people reign over poor people, and people who borrow {money} from others are slaves to the people who loaned them {money}.<verse eid="PRO 22:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 22:8"/>People who act unjustly will suffer for doing so, and they will no longer be able to furiously oppress other people.<verse eid="PRO 22:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 22:9"/>Yahweh will bless generous people because they give their own food to poor people.<verse eid="PRO 22:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 22:10"/>If you banish people who ridicule others, then people will stop arguing {with each other}, quarreling {with each other}, and shaming {each other}.<verse eid="PRO 22:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 22:11"/>People who love thinking purely speak graciously and are companions of kings.<verse eid="PRO 22:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 22:12"/>Yahweh preserves what people should know, but he makes what treacherous people say fail.<verse eid="PRO 22:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 22:13"/>Lazy people {do nothing because they} claim that there is a lion outside that will kill them in the street {if they go outside}.<verse eid="PRO 22:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 22:14"/>What adulterous women say is {as dangerous as} a deep hole; those whom Yahweh is angry with will fall into it.<verse eid="PRO 22:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 22:15"/>Children inherently think foolishly, but physically disciplining them will teach them to stop being foolish.<verse eid="PRO 22:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 22:16"/>People who oppress poor people in order to make more money for themselves or who give things to rich people {in order to become rich} will only become poor.<verse eid="PRO 22:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 22:17"/>Listen carefully to what wise people have said; consider carefully what I am teaching you!<verse eid="PRO 22:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 22:18"/>{Do this} because if you remember these sayings and are always ready to repeat them {to others}, then you will be glad.<verse eid="PRO 22:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 22:19"/>I am teaching these sayings to you—yes, you—right now so that you will trust Yahweh.<verse eid="PRO 22:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 22:20"/>I am indeed writing these 30 sayings to advise and teach you.<verse eid="PRO 22:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 22:21"/>{I am writing them} in order to teach you what is true in trustworthy sayings, and in order to answer those who sent you with trustworthy sayings.<verse eid="PRO 22:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 22:22"/>Do not steal from poor people just because they are poor; and do not oppress suffering people in court.<verse eid="PRO 22:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 22:23"/>{Do not do these things} because Yahweh will defend those poor people when you dispute with them, and he will kill the people who stole from them.<verse eid="PRO 22:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 22:24"/>Do not become friends with angry people. Indeed, do not associate with people who easily become angry.<verse eid="PRO 22:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 22:25"/>{If you do so,} then you will act like them, and you will endanger yourself like an animal caught in a trap.<verse eid="PRO 22:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 22:26"/>Stay away from those people who agree to pay loans for others. {Indeed, stay away from those people} who guarantee to pay the loans of others.<verse eid="PRO 22:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 22:27"/>{For} if you cannot pay back {the loan}, {then} the person to whom you owe money will surely take away even your own bed {in order to pay back the loan}.<verse eid="PRO 22:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 22:28"/>Do not cheat people by moving the stones that their ancestors placed long ago to mark the boundaries of their land.<verse eid="PRO 22:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 22:29"/>Consider this: People who work skillfully will serve kings rather than serving unknown people.<verse eid="PRO 22:29"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 22"/>
<chapter number="23" style="c" sid="PRO 23"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 23:1"/>When you sit down to eat {a meal} with someone who rules over others, pay attention to the food that is in front of you.<verse eid="PRO 23:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 23:2"/>Restrain yourself {from eating too much} if you like eating a lot of food.<verse eid="PRO 23:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 23:3"/>Do not crave the {expensive} food that the ruler has because that ruler is using that food to deceive you.<verse eid="PRO 23:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 23:4"/>Do not work so much that you exhaust yourself in order to become rich. Be understanding enough to stop doing so.<verse eid="PRO 23:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 23:5"/>As soon as you look at that wealth, it will surely be gone! {This is} because wealth certainly disappears quickly as if it had wings and flew off into the sky like a fast bird.<verse eid="PRO 23:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 23:6"/>Do not eat food that stingy people {give you}. Do not crave the expensive food that they have,<verse eid="PRO 23:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 23:7"/>because stingy people are always thinking about how much the food costs them. They will tell you to eat and drink, but they do not mean what they say.<verse eid="PRO 23:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 23:8"/>{When you realize this,} you will want to vomit what little food you ate. You will have wasted the kind things you said {to them}.<verse eid="PRO 23:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 23:9"/>Do not directly address foolish people because they will only despise the insightful things that you say.<verse eid="PRO 23:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 23:10"/>Do not cheat people by moving the old stones that mark the boundaries of their land. Do not claim the land that belongs to {defenseless} orphans,<verse eid="PRO 23:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 23:11"/>because {Yahweh is} the one who redeems them (and he} is powerful. He is the one who will defend them when they dispute with you.<verse eid="PRO 23:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 23:12"/>Consider carefully {what people say} when they correct you. Indeed, listen carefully to what people teach you.<verse eid="PRO 23:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 23:13"/>Do not refuse to discipline your children. If you physically punish them, they will not die.<verse eid="PRO 23:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 23:14"/>Physically punish your children, so that you may prevent them from dying.<verse eid="PRO 23:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 23:15"/>My child, if you are wise, then surely I myself will be very happy,<verse eid="PRO 23:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 23:16"/>and I will sincerely rejoice when you say what is right.<verse eid="PRO 23:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 23:17"/>Do not envy sinful people; instead always reverently fear Yahweh.<verse eid="PRO 23:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 23:18"/>{If you do so, then} you will surely have a {good} future, and what you hope will happen will indeed occur!<verse eid="PRO 23:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 23:19"/>My child, listen {to me} so that you can become wise. Make yourself think about behaving rightly.<verse eid="PRO 23:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 23:20"/>Stay away from drunkards and gluttons,<verse eid="PRO 23:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 23:21"/>because drunkards and gluttons will become poor. They sleep so much that they will only have rags to wear.<verse eid="PRO 23:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 23:22"/>Pay attention to your father, who enabled you to exist, and do not scorn your mother when she becomes old.<verse eid="PRO 23:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 23:23"/>Learn what is true and remember it. Learn what is wise and instructive and what you should understand.<verse eid="PRO 23:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 23:24"/>Fathers of righteous people are very joyful. Indeed, those who father wise people are happy because of them.<verse eid="PRO 23:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 23:25"/>So do what will make your parents happy! Do what will make your mother joyful!<verse eid="PRO 23:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 23:26"/>My son, pay close attention to me! Carefully observe what I do!<verse eid="PRO 23:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 23:27"/>{Do this} because prostitutes are as dangerous as a deep hole. Indeed, adulterous women are as dangerous as a well you cannot escape from.<verse eid="PRO 23:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 23:28"/>These very women certainly wait {for men to seduce} like robbers {wait for people to rob}. They cause many men to become unfaithful.<verse eid="PRO 23:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 23:29"/>These are the kind of people who  are woeful, sorrowful, and quarrelsome, who lament, get hurt for no reason, and have red eyes:<verse eid="PRO 23:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 23:30"/>those people who drink too much wine and are always looking around for wine {to drink} that someone has prepared.<verse eid="PRO 23:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 23:31"/>Do not {even} look with pleasure at wine, even though it is beautifully red, glistens in the cup, and goes down your throat smoothly.<verse eid="PRO 23:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 23:32"/>Afterward the wine {only} harms you as if a poisonous snake had bitten you.<verse eid="PRO 23:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 23:33"/>{When you are drunk,} you will hallucinate, and you will speak perversely.<verse eid="PRO 23:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="PRO 23:34"/>You will feel {dizzy} as if you were trying to sleep on a ship that the sea was tossing back and forth. Indeed, you will feel as if you were trying to sleep while swaying at the top of a ship’s sails.<verse eid="PRO 23:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="PRO 23:35"/>{You will say,} “People hit me, but it did not hurt. People beat me, but I did not feel it. I wish I could be sober so that I could find even more wine {to drink} again!”<verse eid="PRO 23:35"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 23"/>
<chapter number="24" style="c" sid="PRO 24"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 24:1"/>Do not envy evil people; do not want to associate with them,<verse eid="PRO 24:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 24:2"/>because they plan to act violently, and they talk about troubling people.<verse eid="PRO 24:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 24:3"/>People build houses by acting wisely, they make houses stable by acting understandably.<verse eid="PRO 24:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 24:4"/>By acting knowledgeably, people fill the rooms {of those houses} with all kinds of valuable and delightful riches.<verse eid="PRO 24:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 24:5"/>Wise people are strong, and knowledgeable people make themselves more powerful,<verse eid="PRO 24:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 24:6"/>because letting people advise you will make you fight your war successfully, and letting many people counsel you will rescue you {from losing the war}.<verse eid="PRO 24:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 24:7"/>Foolish people cannot understand what is wise; they have nothing to say in court.<verse eid="PRO 24:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 24:8"/>{Some} people are always planning to act evilly; other people refer to them as schemers.<verse eid="PRO 24:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 24:9"/>Foolish plans are sinful, and people detest people who ridicule others.<verse eid="PRO 24:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 24:10"/>If you fail during distressful times, then you are weak.<verse eid="PRO 24:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 24:11"/>Save people whom others are {unjustly} leading away to kill; prevent them from staggering to {the place where} people will {unjustly} slaughter them!<verse eid="PRO 24:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 24:12"/>If you {falsely} claim that you did not know that those people were dying unjustly, then think about this: Yahweh discerns what people think and surely understands! He keeps you alive and surely knows! He will surely make people receive what they deserve for what they have done!<verse eid="PRO 24:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 24:13"/>My child, eat honey because it tastes good, and honey dripping from the comb tastes sweet.<verse eid="PRO 24:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 24:14"/>Be aware that what is wise is like honey for you. If you become wise, then you will have a {good} future, and what you hope will happen will indeed occur!<verse eid="PRO 24:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 24:15"/>Do not be like wicked people and hide in wait in order to attack the places where righteous people dwell. Do not devastate the places where righteous people rest!<verse eid="PRO 24:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 24:16"/>{Do not do so} because righteous people can recover many times when disastrous things happen to them, but disastrous things will destroy wicked people.<verse eid="PRO 24:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 24:17"/>Do not be happy when something disastrous happens to your adversaries. Indeed, do not rejoice when that happens!<verse eid="PRO 24:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 24:18"/>If you do, then Yahweh will notice and disapprove, so that he stops being angry with your enemies.<verse eid="PRO 24:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 24:19"/>Do not worry about people who do what is evil. Do not be jealous of wicked people.<verse eid="PRO 24:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 24:20"/>{Do not do so} because evil people will not have {good} futures, {but} wicked people {will merely die} like an oil lamp that stops burning {oil}.<verse eid="PRO 24:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 24:21"/>My child, reverently fear Yahweh and kings. Avoid people who rebel {against either Yahweh or the king},<verse eid="PRO 24:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 24:22"/>because disastrous things will happen quickly to those people, and no one knows how terribly both Yahweh and kings can destroy {others}!<verse eid="PRO 24:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 24:23"/>Here are more things that wise people have said: It is very evil to favor someone when you judge.<verse eid="PRO 24:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 24:24"/>Many people will curse and people groups will hate anyone who declares that any guilty person is innocent.<verse eid="PRO 24:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 24:25"/>However, people who condemn {guilty people} will prosper, and Yahweh will bless them well.<verse eid="PRO 24:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 24:26"/>People who answer honestly show that they are true friends.<verse eid="PRO 24:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 24:27"/>Do the work you must do outside and prepare your fields before you build your house.<verse eid="PRO 24:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 24:28"/>Do not testify against someone you know if you do not have a good reason {to do so}. Do not speak deceitfully!<verse eid="PRO 24:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 24:29"/>Do not say, “I will do to him that same {bad} thing he did to me; I will pay him back for what he did to me!”<verse eid="PRO 24:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 24:30"/>I walked by the land of a lazy person and past the vineyard of someone who does not think wisely.<verse eid="PRO 24:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 24:31"/>And I saw that thistles and weeds  were everywhere in that field and vineyard. Even the stone wall surrounding them had fallen down.<verse eid="PRO 24:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 24:32"/>When I saw {that}, I considered carefully {what I was seeing}. When I observed {that}, I learned {this}:<verse eid="PRO 24:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 24:33"/>{You say to yourself,} “Let me sleep just a little more! Let me lay my hands {across my chest} in order to rest comfortably for a little while longer!”<verse eid="PRO 24:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="PRO 24:34"/>{Being so lazy} will result in you suddenly becoming poor and needy as if a thief has attacked you.<verse eid="PRO 24:34"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 24"/>
<chapter number="25" style="c" sid="PRO 25"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 25:1"/>Here are more wise sayings said by Solomon that the scribes who served Hezekiah, the king of Judah, copied {from a scroll that Solomon had written}:<verse eid="PRO 25:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 25:2"/>God shows how glorious he is when he makes something difficult for people to understand. But kings show how glorious they are when they explain something {that is difficult for people to understand}.<verse eid="PRO 25:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 25:3"/>As people cannot fully understand how high the sky is or how deep the earth is, so they cannot fully understand what kings think.<verse eid="PRO 25:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 25:4"/>People who make things from metal must remove scum from silver before they can make {that silver into} something.<verse eid="PRO 25:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 25:5"/>{In the same way,} people must remove wicked advisers from the presence of kings before acting righteously causes kings to rule securely.<verse eid="PRO 25:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 25:6"/>Do not promote yourself in front of kings, and do not pretend to be great.<verse eid="PRO 25:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 25:7"/>{Do not do so} because it is better if someone invites you to come closer {to a king}, than for someone to embarrass you in front of a royal official whom you have seen {by telling you to move away from a king}.<verse eid="PRO 25:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 25:8"/>Do not plead your case too quickly against someone you know. If you do, then you will not know what to do when that person {wins the case and} embarrasses you!<verse eid="PRO 25:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 25:9"/>If you do indeed plead your case against someone you know, then do not tell {others} what is secret about that person.<verse eid="PRO 25:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 25:10"/>If do you, then people may hear you and disgrace you, and people will continue to speak badly about you.<verse eid="PRO 25:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 25:11"/>What someone says aptly is {as delightful as} golden apples that someone has set in silver.<verse eid="PRO 25:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 25:12"/>When someone wisely rebukes someone who is willing to listen, it is {as valuable as} a gold ring or jewelry made from the best gold.<verse eid="PRO 25:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 25:13"/>Reliable messengers are as refreshing to those who sent them as cold snow at the time when people harvest crops; they refresh the people whom they serve.<verse eid="PRO 25:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 25:14"/>People who brag about giving something that they never gave are as disappointing as clouds and wind that do not bring rain.<verse eid="PRO 25:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 25:15"/>People can persuade leaders by acting patiently, and by speaking gently people can convince those who oppose them {to agree with them}.<verse eid="PRO 25:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 25:16"/>If you discover some wild honey, do not eat too much of it. If you do, then you will become sick and vomit.<verse eid="PRO 25:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 25:17"/>{In the same way,} do not visit too often the houses of people you know. If you do, then they may become weary of you or {even} hate you.<verse eid="PRO 25:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 25:18"/>People who lie when they testify against people they know are {deadly, like} a club, sword, or piercing arrow.<verse eid="PRO 25:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 25:19"/>Trusting treacherous people during distressful times is {as useless as having} a rotten tooth or a crippled foot.<verse eid="PRO 25:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 25:20"/>Singing to someone who is sad is {as unhelpful as} taking a coat off of someone in cold weather or pouring vinegar on soda.<verse eid="PRO 25:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 25:21"/>Feed your enemies if they are hungry; give them something to drink if they are thirsty.<verse eid="PRO 25:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 25:22"/>{Do so} because by doing so you {will shame them, as if you} are pouring burning coals on top of them, and Yahweh will reward you {for doing so}.<verse eid="PRO 25:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 25:23"/>When wind blows from the north, rain will fall. In the same way, when people tell the secrets of others, people get angry.<verse eid="PRO 25:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 25:24"/>It is better to live {alone} in a corner of a housetop than to live inside a house with a wife who always argues {with you}.<verse eid="PRO 25:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 25:25"/>When people hear something good from a faraway place, it is as {refreshing as drinking} cold water when you are thirsty.<verse eid="PRO 25:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 25:26"/>When righteous people yield to wicked people, it is {as bad as} a spring that people have made murky by walking in it or {as bad as} a polluted fountain.<verse eid="PRO 25:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 25:27"/>{As} it is very bad to eat too much honey; so it is dishonorable to try to make people honor you.<verse eid="PRO 25:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 25:28"/>People who cannot control themselves are {as defenseless as} a city that an army has broken into and knocked down its walls.<verse eid="PRO 25:28"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 25"/>
<chapter number="26" style="c" sid="PRO 26"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 26:1"/>Honoring foolish people is just as inappropriate as snow {falling} in {hot} summer and rain {falling} during the time to harvest crops.<verse eid="PRO 26:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 26:2"/>When someone curses innocent people, it is like birds that fly around and do not land {on those innocent people}.<verse eid="PRO 26:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 26:3"/>As people must whip horses and bridle donkeys {in order to guide them}, so people must physically punish foolish people {in order to guide them}.<verse eid="PRO 26:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 26:4"/>{Sometimes,} do not reply to foolish people according to their foolish way of thinking. If you do, then you also will be foolish.<verse eid="PRO 26:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 26:5"/>{Sometimes,} reply to foolish people according to their foolish way of thinking. If you do not, then they may think that they are wise.<verse eid="PRO 26:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 26:6"/>People who send foolish people to tell {someone else} something on their behalf {harm themselves like} someone who cuts off his own feet or drinks what is harmful.<verse eid="PRO 26:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 26:7"/>{As} the legs of people who cannot walk are useless, so are the sayings that foolish people say.<verse eid="PRO 26:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 26:8"/>Honoring foolish people is just {as useless} as a harmless weapon.<verse eid="PRO 26:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 26:9"/>{As} a thistle that pierces the hand of a drunk person {hurts that person}, so are the sayings that foolish people say.<verse eid="PRO 26:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 26:10"/>People who employ foolish people or random strangers are {as dangerous} as someone who injures all the people {near him} by shooting arrows {at them}.<verse eid="PRO 26:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 26:11"/>Foolish people who do the same foolish thing over and over again are like dogs that eat what they have vomited up.<verse eid="PRO 26:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 26:12"/>Consider this: Foolish people are more likely to improve themselves than people who {wrongly} think they are wise.<verse eid="PRO 26:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 26:13"/>Lazy people {do nothing because they} claim that there is a lion in the path or in the midst of the streets.<verse eid="PRO 26:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 26:14"/>As doors swing on their hinges {and do not go anywhere}, so lazy people turn back and forth in their beds.<verse eid="PRO 26:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 26:15"/>Lazy people put their hands in a dish {of food}, {but} they are so lazy that they will not lift the food to their mouths.<verse eid="PRO 26:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 26:16"/>Lazy people {wrongly} think that they are wiser than many people who answer discreetly.<verse eid="PRO 26:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 26:17"/>People who make themselves angry because of something not concerning them that other people are arguing about are {as foolish as} people who cause dogs to bite them by pulling their ears when they walk by.<verse eid="PRO 26:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 26:18"/>(18-19) People who trick people they know and say that they were just joking are {as dangerous} as a crazy person who {uses a bow to} shoot flaming darks or deadly arrows {at people}.<verse eid="PRO 26:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 26:20"/>Fires stop burning when they have nothing {to burn}. In the same way, people stop arguing when no one is gossiping.<verse eid="PRO 26:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 26:21"/>{As} charcoal keeps coals burning and wood keeps fires burning, so people who always argue keep other people arguing.<verse eid="PRO 26:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 26:22"/>People are eager to listen to what people who gossip say, and what they say deeply affects those who hear it.<verse eid="PRO 26:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 26:23"/>What people fervently say while thinking evilly is {as deceptive as} a cheap pot that someone has covered with a pretty coating.<verse eid="PRO 26:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 26:24"/>People who hate you will use what they say to hide what they feel, but they are {really} thinking about how to betray you.<verse eid="PRO 26:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 26:25"/>Do not believe those people when they speak kindly to you, because they are thinking many detestable things.<verse eid="PRO 26:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 26:26"/>Although those people prevent others from knowing that they hate you by deceiving them, everyone will realize how wicked they are.<verse eid="PRO 26:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 26:27"/>People who dig pits to trap others will fall into those pits instead; and people who try to crush others with stones will become crushed by those stones instead.<verse eid="PRO 26:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 26:28"/>Liars hate the people whom they hurt, and flatterers cause disastrous things to happen.<verse eid="PRO 26:28"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 26"/>
<chapter number="27" style="c" sid="PRO 27"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 27:1"/>Do not brag about what {you think} will happen tomorrow, because you do not know what will happen then.<verse eid="PRO 27:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 27:2"/>Do not praise yourself; let someone else praise you. Indeed, let someone who does not know you praise you, not yourself.<verse eid="PRO 27:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 27:3"/>Stones and sand are heavy, but how provocative fools are is like something that is heavier than both of them.<verse eid="PRO 27:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 27:4"/>Angry people are cruel and furious people are destructive, but no one can resist jealous people!<verse eid="PRO 27:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 27:5"/>It is better to correct people openly, than to love them without them knowing that you do.<verse eid="PRO 27:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 27:6"/>Friends will be faithful to you by criticizing you {when necessary}, but enemies will deceive you by acting affectionately toward you.<verse eid="PRO 27:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 27:7"/>When people who have full stomachs see {on the ground} honey dripping from the comb, they step on it {because they are not hungry}. but even bitter things taste sweet to hungry people {because they are so hungry}.<verse eid="PRO 27:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 27:8"/>People who stray from their homes are like birds that stray from their nests.<verse eid="PRO 27:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 27:9"/>Just as fragrant oil and perfume make people feel happy, so when your friends advise you sincerely, they show how kind they are.<verse eid="PRO 27:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 27:10"/>Do not abandon your friends or your father’s friends. Do not go to the houses of your relatives when something disastrous happens to you. {Rather,} it is better to go to a neighbor than to relatives who live far away.<verse eid="PRO 27:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 27:11"/>My child, act wisely and make me happy, so that I will be able to reply to anyone who argues against me.<verse eid="PRO 27:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 27:12"/>Sensible people observe something dangerous happening and avoid it, but naive people {ignorantly} do not avoid it and suffer {for doing so}.<verse eid="PRO 27:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 27:13"/>Take the coats of people who promise to pay a loan for someone whom they do not know. Indeed, hold onto the coats of people who do so for a foreigner.<verse eid="PRO 27:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 27:14"/>People will think that someone they know is cursing them if that person speaks loudly to bless them early in the morning.<verse eid="PRO 27:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 27:15"/>A wife who always argues {with you} is as {annoying as} constantly dripping water on a rainy day.<verse eid="PRO 27:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 27:16"/>It is as difficult to stop her {from arguing} as stopping the wind, or catching oil in one hand.<verse eid="PRO 27:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 27:17"/>Just as iron can sharpen an iron {blade}, so too people can help people they know improve how they think.<verse eid="PRO 27:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 27:18"/>Just as people who take care of fruit trees will eat the fruit from those trees {as a result}, so too will masters honor their servants who guard them.<verse eid="PRO 27:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 27:19"/>When people look in water, the water reflects their faces. In the same way, what people think reveals what kinds of people they are.<verse eid="PRO 27:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 27:20"/>Just as the place where dead people go never becomes full; so people never stop wanting {something}.<verse eid="PRO 27:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 27:21"/>People use crucibles and furnaces to test and refine silver and gold. In the same way, people test what kind of person someone is by saying good things about that person.<verse eid="PRO 27:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 27:22"/>If you were to crush a fool the way you would crush grain {into powder}, you would still not be able to stop that person from acting foolishly.<verse eid="PRO 27:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 27:23"/>Be fully aware of how your sheep are doing. Indeed, consider carefully how your animals fare.<verse eid="PRO 27:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 27:24"/>{Do so} because riches will not last forever. Even a king’s family will not rule forever!<verse eid="PRO 27:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 27:25"/>Harvest the grass and then you will see new grass. Collect {and store} the plants that grow on the hillside.<verse eid="PRO 27:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 27:26"/>{If you do these things, then} you will have lambs with wool that you can clothe yourself with. You will also have male goats that you can sell for enough money to buy a field.<verse eid="PRO 27:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 27:27"/>You will even have female goats that produce enough milk for yourself, your family, and your servant girls to drink.<verse eid="PRO 27:27"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 27"/>
<chapter number="28" style="c" sid="PRO 28"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 28:1"/>Wicked people run away even though no one is chasing them, but righteous people are as brave as lions.<verse eid="PRO 28:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 28:2"/>When the people in a country sin, they have many leaders; but when they have a truly knowledgeable ruler, they will last.<verse eid="PRO 28:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 28:3"/>Poor people who oppress other poor people are {as destructive as} rain that destroys all the crops, so that there is nothing to eat.<verse eid="PRO 28:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 28:4"/>People who reject {Yahweh’s} laws say good things about wicked people; but people who obey those laws oppose such wicked people.<verse eid="PRO 28:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 28:5"/>Evil people cannot comprehend what is just, but people who desire to please Yahweh comprehend everything about it.<verse eid="PRO 28:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 28:6"/>It is better to be poor and act honestly than to act dishonestly and be rich.<verse eid="PRO 28:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 28:7"/>People who obey {Yahweh’s} laws are discerning children, but people who befriend gluttons disgrace their fathers.<verse eid="PRO 28:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 28:8"/>People who become wealthy by charging an unreasonably large amount of interest {from those to whom they loan money} {unknowingly} collect that wealth to give it to people who are kind to poor people.<verse eid="PRO 28:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 28:9"/>Yahweh detests what people pray if those people refuse to even listen to his laws.<verse eid="PRO 28:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 28:10"/>People who guide upright people to act evilly will destroy themselves by what they do, but people whom Yahweh does not blame {for acting wickedly} will receive what is good.<verse eid="PRO 28:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 28:11"/>Rich people may {wrongly} think that they are wise, but discerning poor people will prove that those people are not {wise}.<verse eid="PRO 28:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 28:12"/>People celebrate when righteous people become powerful, but people hide when wicked people become powerful.<verse eid="PRO 28:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 28:13"/>People who {try to} hide the sinful things that they do will never be successful, but Yahweh will be merciful to people who confess the sinful things that they have done and stop doing them.<verse eid="PRO 28:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 28:14"/>People who always reverently fear Yahweh are happy, but bad things happen to stubborn people.<verse eid="PRO 28:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 28:15"/>Wicked people who rule over poor people are {as dangerous as} a roaring lion or attacking bear.<verse eid="PRO 28:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 28:16"/>Leaders who are not understanding severely oppress {other people}, {but} people who despise gaining wealth unjustly will live for a long time.<verse eid="PRO 28:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 28:17"/>People who murder others will keep running away {from those who would punish them} until they die. Do not help them!<verse eid="PRO 28:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 28:18"/>Yahweh will rescue people whom he does not blame for how they act, but people who act dishonestly will suddenly ruin themselves.<verse eid="PRO 28:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 28:19"/>People who work hard will have enough food {to eat}, but people who waste time doing worthless things will only be poor.<verse eid="PRO 28:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 28:20"/>Yahweh abundantly blesses faithful people, but he will certainly punish people who are eager to be wealthy.<verse eid="PRO 28:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 28:21"/>Although it is very evil to favor someone, some people will sin {by doing so} to get as little as a scrap of food.<verse eid="PRO 28:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 28:22"/>Although people who are eager to become rich are stingy, they do not realize that they will become poor.<verse eid="PRO 28:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 28:23"/>People approve of someone who corrects them after that person does so more than {they might approve of} someone who speaks flatteringly {to them}.<verse eid="PRO 28:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 28:24"/>People who rob their parents and say that doing so is not wrong are as bad as murderers.<verse eid="PRO 28:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 28:25"/>Greedy people cause people to argue with each other, but Yahweh will prosper people who trust him.<verse eid="PRO 28:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 28:26"/>People who trust themselves are foolish, but people who act wisely are the ones who will escape {what is dangerous}.<verse eid="PRO 28:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 28:27"/>People who give poor people {what they need} will have all that they need, but Yahweh abundantly curses people who ignore poor people.<verse eid="PRO 28:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 28:28"/>People hide when wicked people become powerful, but when those wicked people die, there will be more and more righteous people.<verse eid="PRO 28:28"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 28"/>
<chapter number="29" style="c" sid="PRO 29"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 29:1"/>Some people become stubborn when other people correct them, someone will destroy them instantly and they will not be able to recover.<verse eid="PRO 29:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 29:2"/>People are joyful when righteous people become numerous, but people are miserable when wicked people rule {over them}.<verse eid="PRO 29:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 29:3"/>People who cherish what is wise make their fathers happy, but people who have sex with prostitutes waste all their money.<verse eid="PRO 29:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 29:4"/>Kings make the people in their land succeed by acting justly, but leaders who take money dishonestly ruin the people in their land.<verse eid="PRO 29:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 29:5"/>People who flatter people they know {are deceptive}, {they are like} people who try to trap others.<verse eid="PRO 29:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 29:6"/>Evil people endanger themselves by acting sinfully, but righteous people sing joyfully and are happy.<verse eid="PRO 29:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 29:7"/>Righteous people care about the rights of poor people, but wicked people do not care about them at all.<verse eid="PRO 29:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 29:8"/>People who mock others agitate people living in a city, but wise people stop others from being angry.<verse eid="PRO 29:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 29:9"/>If wise people sue foolish people, the foolish people will rage and sneer and not resolve anything.<verse eid="PRO 29:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 29:10"/>Murderers despise people whom Yahweh does not blame {for acting wickedly}, but upright people try to protect those people.<verse eid="PRO 29:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 29:11"/>Foolish people uncontrollably express everything that they feel, but wise people control how they express what they feel.<verse eid="PRO 29:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 29:12"/>Leaders who believe the false things that people tell them have only wicked servants.<verse eid="PRO 29:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 29:13"/>Poor people and the people who oppress {them} have {at least} one thing in common: Yahweh is the one who caused them to live.<verse eid="PRO 29:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 29:14"/>Kings who judge poor people according to what is true will always rule securely.<verse eid="PRO 29:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 29:15"/>If parents punish and correct their children, doing so can make those children wise; but if parents let their children do whatever they want to do, then their children will disgrace them.<verse eid="PRO 29:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 29:16"/>People sin more when wicked people become numerous, but righteous people will witness Yahweh destroy those wicked people.<verse eid="PRO 29:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 29:17"/>Discipline your children, so that they will make you feel peaceful and will delight you.<verse eid="PRO 29:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 29:18"/>When Yahweh does not reveal anything {to his prophets}, then people do not control themselves, but people who obey {Yahweh’s} laws are happy.<verse eid="PRO 29:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 29:19"/>You cannot correct servants by {only} speaking to them because they will not respond to you, even if they understand {what you say}.<verse eid="PRO 29:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 29:20"/>Consider this: Foolish people are more likely to improve themselves than people who speak thoughtlessly.<verse eid="PRO 29:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 29:21"/>If you give your servants everything they want when they are young, then they will eventually be arrogant.<verse eid="PRO 29:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 29:22"/>People who easily become angry cause people to argue. Indeed, angry people cause people to sin.<verse eid="PRO 29:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 29:23"/>People will humiliate proud people for being proud, but people will honor humble people.<verse eid="PRO 29:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 29:24"/>People who help thieves only hurt themselves. They hear that Yahweh will curse them {for not speaking what is true}, but they do not say anything.<verse eid="PRO 29:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 29:25"/>Being anxious is {as dangerous as} a trap, but people who trust Yahweh will be safe.<verse eid="PRO 29:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 29:26"/>Many people want leaders to help them, but Yahweh is the only one who does what is just for them.<verse eid="PRO 29:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 29:27"/>Righteous people detest unjust people, but wicked people detest people who act uprightly.<verse eid="PRO 29:27"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 29"/>
<chapter number="30" style="c" sid="PRO 30"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 30:1"/>{These are} the sayings of Agur son of Jakeh, which Yahweh told him to say; {these are what} Agur declared to Ithiel, even to Ithiel and Ucal:<verse eid="PRO 30:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 30:2"/>I am certainly less intelligent than other people. Indeed, I do not understand as much as everyone else understands!<verse eid="PRO 30:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 30:3"/>I have never learned about what is wise, nor do I know about {Yahweh,} the Holy One.<verse eid="PRO 30:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 30:4"/>Surely nobody has ever gone to heaven and returned to earth! Surely nobody has ever controlled the wind! Surely nobody has ever gathered the water for rain in the clouds! Surely nobody has ever formed the boundaries of the earth! {If such a person exists, then} what is his name? And what is the name of his son? Surely you do not know {about such a person}!<verse eid="PRO 30:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 30:5"/>Everything that God says is true; he is {like} a shield that protects people who trust him to protect them.<verse eid="PRO 30:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 30:6"/>Never claim that God has said something other than what he has {actually} said. If you do that, then he will correct you and he will prove that you lied {about what he said}.<verse eid="PRO 30:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 30:7"/>I ask Yahweh for two things, and ask that he give them to me before I die:<verse eid="PRO 30:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 30:8"/>{I ask that he} prevent me from being dishonest or speaking what is not true. {I also ask that he} not let me become too poor or too rich, {but} just provide the proper amount of food for me.<verse eid="PRO 30:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 30:9"/>If I become too rich, then I may reject Yahweh and claim that I do not know him. Or if I become too poor, then I may rob {other people}, so that I dishonor my God.<verse eid="PRO 30:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 30:10"/>Never say bad things about servants to the people whom they serve. If you do, then they will curse you, and people will hold you responsible {for what you said}.<verse eid="PRO 30:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 30:11"/>Some people frequently curse their parents.<verse eid="PRO 30:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 30:12"/>Some people think they are sinless, but they are {actually guilty like} people who have not cleaned off their filth.<verse eid="PRO 30:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 30:13"/>Some people are extremely arrogant!<verse eid="PRO 30:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 30:14"/>Some people {harshly oppress poor people as if they} were animals who remove poor people from the world by eating them up with very sharp teeth.<verse eid="PRO 30:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 30:15"/>{Greedy people are like} animals that suck blood and have two daughters. {The names of both of them are} Give Me Some! There are three, no, four things that always want more:<verse eid="PRO 30:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 30:16"/>the place where dead people are, childless women, soil that never receives enough water, and fire, which always needs something to burn.<verse eid="PRO 30:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 30:17"/>People who ridicule their fathers, and refuse to obey their mothers {will die and} wild birds will pluck out their eyes, and young scavenging birds will eat them.<verse eid="PRO 30:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 30:18"/>There are three, no, four things that are too amazing for me to comprehend:<verse eid="PRO 30:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 30:19"/>how birds fly in the air, how snakes slither over rocks, how ships sail in the middle of the ocean, and how young men act {lovingly} with young women.<verse eid="PRO 30:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 30:20"/>Acting adulterously is {as easy} for adulterous women as eating, wiping their mouths, and claiming that they have not sinned at all.<verse eid="PRO 30:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 30:21"/>There are three, no, four things that {the people in} the world cannot tolerate:<verse eid="PRO 30:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 30:22"/>when slaves become rulers, when worthless people have plenty of food to eat,<verse eid="PRO 30:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 30:23"/>when women whom people hate marry someone, and when servant girls replace the wives of their masters.<verse eid="PRO 30:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 30:24"/>There are four creatures in the world that are small but extremely wise:<verse eid="PRO 30:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 30:25"/>Although ants are weak insects, during the right time they store their food {to eat during the winter}.<verse eid="PRO 30:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 30:26"/>Although hyraxes are weak animals, they make their homes {among the rocks} on cliffs.<verse eid="PRO 30:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 30:27"/>Although locusts do not have a king, they move in orderly groups like soldiers in an army.<verse eid="PRO 30:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 30:28"/>Although lizards are small enough to hold in your hands, you can find them inside kings’ palaces.<verse eid="PRO 30:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 30:29"/>There are three, no, four things that look very impressive when they walk:<verse eid="PRO 30:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 30:30"/>lions, which are the most powerful animals and never flee from anything,<verse eid="PRO 30:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 30:31"/>strutting male birds, male goats, and kings whom people are afraid to rebel against.<verse eid="PRO 30:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="PRO 30:32"/>If you have acted foolishly by bragging about yourself, or if you were plotting {to do what is evil}, then stop doing so immediately!<verse eid="PRO 30:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="PRO 30:33"/>{Stop doing so} because {doing so will cause bad things to happen to you,} just as churning milking turns it into butter, squeezing a nose will make it bleed, and making people angry causes them to fight.<verse eid="PRO 30:33"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 30"/>
<chapter number="31" style="c" sid="PRO 31"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="PRO 31:1"/>{These are} the sayings of King Lemuel; Yahweh had spoken these sayings that his mother had taught him:<verse eid="PRO 31:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="PRO 31:2"/>My son, whom I gave birth to and whom I vowed {to dedicate to Yahweh}, listen to me!<verse eid="PRO 31:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="PRO 31:3"/>Do not exhaust yourself by having sex with women; they can destroy kings.<verse eid="PRO 31:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="PRO 31:4"/>Lemuel, kings should certainly not drink wine, and rulers should not want to drink what can intoxicate {them}.”<verse eid="PRO 31:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="PRO 31:5"/>If they do so, then they might forget the laws {that they have made} and prevent all suffering people from getting what they legally deserve.<verse eid="PRO 31:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="PRO 31:6"/>Let dying people drink what can intoxicate {them}, and let miserable people drink wine.<verse eid="PRO 31:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="PRO 31:7"/>They can drink {what can intoxicate them} to forget that they are poor and to completely forget what troubles them.<verse eid="PRO 31:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="PRO 31:8"/>Defend those who cannot speak {for themselves}; {defend} all those who are dying so that they get what they legally deserve.<verse eid="PRO 31:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="PRO 31:9"/>Defend, judge rightly, and plead for suffering and poor people to get what they legally deserve.<verse eid="PRO 31:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="PRO 31:10"/>Virtuous and capable women are difficult to find! This kind of woman is more valuable than precious jewels.<verse eid="PRO 31:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="PRO 31:11"/>Her husband completely trusts her, and he will always gain many things {because of her}.<verse eid="PRO 31:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="PRO 31:12"/>Such a woman benefits her husband for as long as she lives.<verse eid="PRO 31:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="PRO 31:13"/>She gets materials to make warm and cool clothing, and she enjoys making that clothing.<verse eid="PRO 31:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="PRO 31:14"/>She is like merchant ships because she brings her food to her home from distant places.<verse eid="PRO 31:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="PRO 31:15"/>She gets up before dawn in order to prepare food for her family and some {food} for her female servants.<verse eid="PRO 31:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="PRO 31:16"/>She buys a field after planning carefully. She uses some of what she earned by working to plant a vineyard.<verse eid="PRO 31:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="PRO 31:17"/>She vigorously prepares herself to work hard, and she makes her arms strong {by working hard}.<verse eid="PRO 31:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="PRO 31:18"/>She knows that what she does is very profitable. She works late into the night.<verse eid="PRO 31:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="PRO 31:19"/>She makes thread {for clothing} with her own hands.<verse eid="PRO 31:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="PRO 31:20"/>She helps poor people and suffering people.<verse eid="PRO 31:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="PRO 31:21"/>She is not worried that her family will be cold during cold weather because her whole family has the best warm clothing.<verse eid="PRO 31:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="PRO 31:22"/>She makes her own blankets to cover beds. She wears clothing made from expensive cloth.<verse eid="PRO 31:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="PRO 31:23"/>People respect such a woman’s husband at the {city} gates, and he sits {there} with the {other} leaders of the city.<verse eid="PRO 31:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="PRO 31:24"/>This woman makes clothing and sells it. She also sells belts to merchants.<verse eid="PRO 31:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="PRO 31:25"/>People notice how strong and dignified she is, and she is cheerful about what will happen in the future.<verse eid="PRO 31:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="PRO 31:26"/>She speaks wisely, and when she speaks, she teaches {others} to be faithfully kind.<verse eid="PRO 31:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="PRO 31:27"/>She carefully watches what happens in her household, and she is never lazy.<verse eid="PRO 31:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="PRO 31:28"/>This woman’s children stand respectfully and declare that she lives happily. Her husband says good things about her as well.<verse eid="PRO 31:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="PRO 31:29"/>He says to her, “Many women have acted virtuously and capably, but you indeed have done better than them all!”<verse eid="PRO 31:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="PRO 31:30"/>Charming women {who are not good} can deceive people into thinking that they are good, and beautiful women will not remain beautiful forever. However, people will praise those women who reverently fear Yahweh.<verse eid="PRO 31:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="PRO 31:31"/>Give to such women what they have earned, and praise them publicly for what they have done.<verse eid="PRO 31:31"/></para>
<chapter eid="PRO 31"/>
</usx>